<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The terrestriall paradise, or, Happinesse on earth. Written by Robert  Crofts</title>
            <author>R. C. (Robert Crofts)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1639</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 125 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19611</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6044</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109076</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844726</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844726</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9564</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19611)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9564)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1022:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The terrestriall paradise, or, Happinesse on earth. Written by Robert  Crofts</title>
                  <author>R. C. (Robert Crofts)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[114] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Harper for William Aderton, and are to be sold at his shop in Duck-lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1639.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Partly in verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]¹²  ([A]³+chi¹) B-E¹²  (-A1-3,5).</note>
                  <note>With an additional title page, engraved: "The terrestriall paradise or Happines on earth.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Happiness --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:9564:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9564:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9564:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <hi>THE Terrestriall PARADISE</hi> OR Happines on Earth. <hi>BY</hi> R Crofts.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>London. Printed by T. Harper. for William Adderton. 1639</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9564:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE TERRESTRIALL PARADISE, OR, <hi>Happineſſe on Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written by <hi>Robert Crofts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Thomas Harper</hi> for <hi>William Ader<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> and are to be ſold at
his ſhop in Duck-lane, 1639.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:9564:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9564:3"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO <hi>the Readers.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL men naturally deſire happines All their plots, purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and endevours aime at this
end on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Wherefore it is and alwayes hath been free and very commendable, for all men to learne
<pb facs="tcp:9564:4"/> and ſeek happines in all good ways To tell what they have learn'd and to doe good to
themſelves and others, according to their genius abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, opportunities, and occaſions.
Having therefore had more leiſure then ſometimes I wiſht to have, and therin alſo the
opportunity to peruſe many good Authors, I thought not amiſſe (to avoid idleneſſe and
Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy, and to recreate and pleaſe my ſelfe) to ſearch and ſtudy for true joy and
happineſſe. And having col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected many notes concerning Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtriall, Morall, and divine
happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe on earth, I have ſince written the ſame together in a Booke and as well as my
weakneſſe could, digeſt
<pb facs="tcp:9564:4"/> the ſame into ſuch a manner, method and ſtile, as I thought beſt, with ſuch
alterations, additions, intermixtions, and inventions, as met with my Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations; intending the
ſame at firſt onely for private uſe. I had thought to have written in this Epiſtle divers
reaſons moving mee to publiſh this little Treatiſe before the reſt which I have written of
this ſubject. But if I ſhould, the ſame would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the Epiſtle too long for the Booke:
Nor is it expedient to parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularize, and tell you private reaſons in print, I ſhall now
therfore concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this matter onely tell you, that having lately publiſht a little Booke being
one particular part of <hi>Terreſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb facs="tcp:9564:5"/> Happineſſe</hi> (as this is a generall part therof.) The Epiſtle therein, to the
Reader, may with very little alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſerve to this Book alſo, to which (if you be not
ſatisfied,) I referre you.</p>
            <p>And ſince I have made uſe of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good Authors; And found much happineſſe in the
inquiſition and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy therof, I cannot but hope there are ſome things herein worthy your
peruſing. Nor is it a crime, as ſome would ſeeme to mayntaine, to make uſe of Authours; It
rather argues conceitedneſſe, vain-glory, and folly in ſuch men, who think it Pedanticall and
weakneſſe; to ſtoop to and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge other mens authority and opinions as being oppoſite
to their
<pb facs="tcp:9564:5"/> affected humours and ſtile, when as themſelves indeed gaine all their knowledge
from others. And now, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is ſaid; No new thing can be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten which hath not been before.</p>
            <p>Yet by compoſing a Book in a new manner, method, and ſtile, by alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, adding to,
abridging, and ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times converting to other purpoſes, the ſame may ſeem to be (and be as
uſefull) as if it were all new, and which to doe is often as difficult, and requires wel-nigh as
much art, as wholly the invention of new mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: and is better to be eſteemed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe more
authenticall.</p>
            <p>I ſhould have done well indeed, to have cited Authours, But being at
<pb facs="tcp:9564:6"/> firſt written for private uſe I negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the ſame, and now cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem that
neglect, or if I could the Treatiſe, in reſpect of the ſtile inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixions, abſtractions,
additions, and alterations in divers places would not well admit therof. But although it be truly
ſaid that no new thing, can be ſaid or written which hath not been (to the ſame effect)
before; yet may it be ſaid of this Treatiſe in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall (aſwell of the compoſition
thereof) that the ſame is new, in as much as never any man (that I can reade of) hath written any
Book of this ſubject, Namely, the enjoying of earthly happineſſe freely and cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
(though in the good uſe therof)
<pb facs="tcp:9564:6"/> and with a heavenly minde: But of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e contempt thereof many Bookes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave been written,
and yet the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt contemners of earthly felicities, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their Bookes will ſometimes
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſe this truth, That in the good uſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hereof the ſame may be enjoyed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reely and
cheerfully. And that ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ree enjoying, and the contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns thereof may excite us to Pietie,
to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eavenly joy and happineſſe.</p>
            <p>Concerning the ſtile and method, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> affect not too much niceneſſe and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urioſity. Nor
on the otherſide, too <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch looſeneſſe and indigeſtion. My <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndevours have been to
compoſe the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ame in a ſerious, yet free and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng way. But, I confeſſe, my ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours
<pb facs="tcp:9564:7"/> are very weak and worth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leſſe, whch I tell you; and truly te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you, becauſe I had
much rather yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhould be poſſeſt with a prejudicat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> under opinion, then great
expectati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on; It is eaſier to make the one falſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> then the other true, I could wiſh in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deed,
that I were able to raiſe Medita<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions as high as Heaven from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Earth. But the conſideration
of my weaknes, and unworthineſſe deject<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> me.</p>
            <p>But the Abſtracts, I confeſſe, I have beene but little uſed to ſtudy in tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> way. And
they were but a late exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of a ſhort time for recreation and to try concluſions. In them
alſo I have not much cared for niceneſs o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:9564:7"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urioſity, but take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a free liberty. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ooke were (perchance) in a wiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ans
judgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, better without them. But in my weak judgement the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay be read (as they were
written) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o recreate the minde. Alſo to quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en the memory. They are compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed (conſidering
the ſubject) in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ew and, I hope, pleaſing manner, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd free from unneceſſary Poeticall
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dditions, fained allegories, Parables, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd conſequently from obſcurity, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iouſneſſe,
and moſt befitting the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>bject.</p>
            <p>Concerning the Title, it is uſuall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o prefixe titles to Books in theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>imes, perchance
better then they deſerve, and as ſome thinke, a kinde
<pb facs="tcp:9564:8"/> of policy. If therfore you thinke have herein done amiſſe I have preſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dents for
it. Notwithſtanding; think the Book in divers reſpects i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> correſpondent to the Title, and ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
very well befit the ſame. However would deſire you to expect onely a very ſhort diſcourſe
upon each of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſeverall heads or Sections; a view wherof you may ſee in the Analyſis If you
look for more you are not like in this Book to finde it.</p>
            <p>How neceſſary this Treatiſe is, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe will ſhew. I conceive there can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be a
greater motive to ſtirre us up to vertue and pietie, then to ſhew (againſt the pernitious
opinion of the World conceiting the contrary)
<pb facs="tcp:9564:8"/> that vertuous and pious men even in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is life may enjoy much more hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>neſſe than
vicious impious men. That this truth may more plainly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ppeare, I ſhall endevour hereafter to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ew
the ſame more particularly and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ainly, alſo to ſearch further and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore excellent
Happineſſe, to enjoy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s far as our mindes are capable) on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arth, the joys of Heaven within
us.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Robert Crofts.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="analysis">
            <pb facs="tcp:9564:9"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9564:9"/>
            <head>The Analyſis briefly.</head>
            <p>A view of earthly Happineſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> We ſhould enjoy the ſame
<list>
                  <item>With Contentment,</item>
                  <item>In the good uſe therof,</item>
                  <item>Freely and cheerfully.</item>
                  <item>Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding their
<list>
                        <item>Vanities,</item>
                        <item>Dangers,</item>
                        <item>Impediments, &amp;c</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>With a heavenly minde.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb facs="tcp:9564:10"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:9564:10"/>THE TERRESTRIALL PARADISE, OR, <hi>Happineſſe on Earth.</hi>
         </head>
         <div n="1" type="section">
            <head>
               <hi>The firſt Section.</hi> A view of earthly Happineſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Erreſtriall happineſſe is u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually reduced to theſe three heads, To Riches, Honour,
and Pleaſures: from which as from ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Fountains, all the reſt doth ſpring and
proceed, and he that enjoyes theſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:9564:11"/> may be ſaid to enjoy a Terreſtriall Paradiſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Happineſſe.</p>
            <p>To define the riches of the World, were to tell you what every man knows, the good ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects and
benefits which ſpring from thence are many &amp; divers. Good Education, Acquaintance, Friends,
Lovers, Honour, Authority and many pleaſures of divers ſorts are hereby often occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. So
as many rich men ſeeme to enjoy an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> earthly Paradiſe.</p>
            <p>True honour is defined to be the ſhining brightneſſe of worthy vertuous and gracious
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, reflected from our own conſciences unto the ſight and view of thoſe with whom we
live, it may be alſo called a graceful reſpect or renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned reputation, which every man ought
to have in recompence of his worthineſſe which is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto the World by good and glorious
deeds and approved of, by the acknowledgment of good and vertuous men; and it ſhineth moſt
brightly in ſuch as are of greateſt birth, of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt riches and of greateſt dignity and
authority both in Church and Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>It is not then an imaginary Phantaſie, but a ſplendent brightneſſe, which maketh him
that is the ſubject therof, to ſhine forth as the ſparkling rayes of a Diamond, and for as
much as it procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from vertuous and worthy actions, it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes accompanied with inward joy
and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:9564:11"/> And among noble, good, and great Spirits, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>othing is more deſirous and
pleaſant, inſomuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they will ſpare no labour, no pain, but willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and fearleſly
will adventure through many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ifficulties, many perils to gain the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A good name, ſaith</hi> Solomon, <hi>is better than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>old, and more precious than
ointment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pleaſures are of divers ſorts: all the riches, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our and delights of the World ſerve to
pleaſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur mindes. What a number of excellent plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ures and felicities hath God created in this
Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſtriall Paradiſe which may pleaſe our ſenſes!</p>
            <p>And firſt the ſence of ſeeing, as the Heavens <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir glorious aſpect, the Sun in its
lovely bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the Moon her ſilver rayes, the Stars their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>winkling ſparks, the Aire
its fair nakedneſſe, the Birds enameld with all ſorts of colours, the Trees <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>edeckt with
bloſſomes, fruits and leaves, the medows with Tapeſtry green, the Rivers with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Cryſtall
of their ſtreams, the Sea, it's huge and pleaſant watery Mantle, And an infinite number of
creatures both in the Earth and Sea of different figures, fair and goodly Cities, Towns, Churches,
Houſes, Orchards, Gardens, all plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ant places, and all faire, beautifull, and amiable
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reatures.</p>
            <p>To pleaſe the ſence of hearing alſo, How can wee but be much delighted amidſt the
pleaſures
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:9564:12"/> of a ſweet harmony, either of voices or inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; at the prety purling
of a ſilver brook, the ſweet running murmurs of a pleaſant fountaine, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he pleaſing notes
and prety warbling of Birds, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he amorous accents of a delicate voice, joyned with the ſweet
allurements of the melody of a Lute, the muſicall tun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and delightfull ſtrains of all kinde of
Inſtruments, to heare the pleaſant and gallant noyſes of Bels, Trumpets, Drums, and other
delicious ſounds. Alſo to heare plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Diſcourſes, Hiſtories, Songs, Tales, Ieſts,
News, and the like.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe of the other Senſes, as the taſting of ſweet and delicious meats of all
ſorts, of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and ſparkling wine, and other delightfull li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quours.</p>
            <p>Alſo the ſmelling of odoriferous Perfumes, Flowres of every kinde, and all other ſweet and
fragrant things; there is ſuch a multitude of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights and felicities in the World to pleaſe
the Senſes, as they are innumerable.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe the moſt pleaſant and happy ſocietie of Parents, Children, Wives, Lovers,
Friends, Kindred and acquaintance: And in generall, the enjoyance of riches, honour, all ſorts of
lawfull Sports, Recreations, Delights and Happineſſes; all whatſoever is pleaſant and
delectable.</p>
            <p>Inſomuch, as from divers of theſe particulars
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:9564:12"/> (as might be at large dilated in whole Volumes) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pringeth abundance of ſweet
and pleaſant joys and felicities. Enough to charme, and ſweetly bring our mindes into an
extaſie of joy and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe.</p>
            <p>In all which if wee throughly view them in their number, variety, pleaſantneſſe,
excellencie, and happy effects we may plainly ſee, that even in this life wee may enjoy a
terreſtriall Paradiſe of joy and happineſſe.</p>
            <div type="abstract">
               <head>The abſtract of the firſt SECTION.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THere is within the Earth, ſo many treaſures,</l>
                  <l>Such glorious honors &amp; delightfull pleaſures,</l>
                  <l>That who enjoys all theſe felicities</l>
                  <l>Enjoys indeed, an earthly Paradiſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The riches of the Earth to us do bring</l>
                  <l>Much happineſſe, from thence doth often ſpring</l>
                  <l>So many benefits, honours and pleaſures,</l>
                  <l>As makes us much eſteem theſe earthly treaſures.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Honour likewiſe, Its glorious bright aſpect</l>
                  <l>And ſplendent beauty, doth ſo much attract,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:9564:13"/>All good and great, noble heroick Spirits</l>
                  <l>As that they much deſire by glorious merits,</l>
                  <l>By all good worthy deeds, the ſame to gain</l>
                  <l>For which theyle ſpare no labours, fear no pain.</l>
                  <l>To them nothing is more delightfull, &amp; they deem</l>
                  <l>Nothing on Earth more worthy their eſteem.</l>
                  <l>A good name, ſaith King <hi>Solomon,</hi> is better</l>
                  <l>Then gold, and precious ointment is not ſweeter.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Pleaſures are many, and of divers kindes,</l>
                  <l>The whole world ſeemes to ſerve to pleaſe our minds</l>
                  <l>How many pleaſant ſweet felicities</l>
                  <l>May we enjoy within Earths Paradiſe?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Who can but ſweetly, greatly pleaſed bee,</l>
                  <l>So many lovely, pleaſant ſights to ſee</l>
                  <l>The Sun, Moon, Stars, whoſe glittering heavenly beams</l>
                  <l>Dazle our eyes, likewiſe the ſilver ſtreams</l>
                  <l>Of Rivers, Fountains, prety Birds to ſee,</l>
                  <l>And other creatures, bloſſoms on each tree,</l>
                  <l>Fruits, leaves, the medows, woods &amp; fields ſo green,</l>
                  <l>All pleaſant objects therin to be ſeen,</l>
                  <l>The Sea, the Ships, Cities, Towns, Caſtles fair,</l>
                  <l>Churches and houſes, gardens, beauties rare</l>
                  <l>Gold, Pearles, a thouſand other pleaſing ſights</l>
                  <l>Each one affording us moſt ſweet delights.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:9564:13"/>
                  <l>Likewiſe to charm and to delight the eare</l>
                  <l>Sweet Muſick, pleaſing melody to heare</l>
                  <l>The prety chirping warbling notes of Birds,</l>
                  <l>And purling murmurs of a Brook, affoords</l>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s prety pleaſures, and the melody</l>
                  <l>Of Inſtruments, likewiſe the harmony</l>
                  <l>And delicate accents of an amorous voice,</l>
                  <l>The gallant ſounds of Trumpets pleaſing noiſe,</l>
                  <l>Of Drums and Bels, doth greatly, ſweetly move,</l>
                  <l>And pleaſe our eares; and alſo tales of love</l>
                  <l>And other prety Stories, Jeſts, Songs, News,</l>
                  <l>Do ſweetly charm us in a pleaſing Muſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So likewiſe pleaſant cates, and banqueting diſhes,</l>
                  <l>All ſorts of dainty meats, as fowles and fiſhes,</l>
                  <l>Sweet pleaſing liquors, brisk, neat, ſparkling, fine</l>
                  <l>Canary, and the like delicious wine</l>
                  <l>To pleaſe our taſting ſence, of every kinde</l>
                  <l>Abundance in this Paradiſe we finde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And alſo flowres, perfumes and fragrant things</l>
                  <l>Of divers ſorts, the Earth yields forth and brings</l>
                  <l>To pleaſe the ſence of ſmelling. Inſomuch</l>
                  <l>The pleaſures of the Earth are truly ſuch,</l>
                  <l>So ſweet, ſo many, that if I ſhould tell</l>
                  <l>You what, how ſweet, how many, I ſhould dwell</l>
                  <l>For ever in diſcourſe. It doth ſurmount</l>
                  <l>All pens, all tongues to ſhew, and to recount.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:9564:14"/>
                  <l>The happy pleaſures loving Parents may,</l>
                  <l>And children alſo, mutually enjoy,</l>
                  <l>Each in the other; likewiſe husbands, wives,</l>
                  <l>Lovers and friends even during all their lives</l>
                  <l>Partake together; truly ſo much joy,</l>
                  <l>Such mirth, and ſports, ſuch ſweet delights we ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Enjoy together in our happy love</l>
                  <l>And mutuall pleaſures, that they even may move</l>
                  <l>And bring our mindes with delectation ſweet</l>
                  <l>(Charming the ſame when therin they do meet)</l>
                  <l>Into an extaſis of pleaſure; thus we may</l>
                  <l>A Paradiſe of ſweet delights enjoy.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="section">
            <head>
               <hi>The ſecond Section.</hi> We ought to enjoy earthly happineſſe with
contentment.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving viewed wherein earthly happineſſe conſiſts, now, to the intent we may be further
happy therin, let us endevour to ſettle our minds in a contented eſtate, in all accidents and
conditions, and ſo to enjoy theſe terreſtriall felicities, with a contented happy minde.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:9564:14"/>It is ſtrange that ſome have put this truth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a Paradox, That he
forſooth is the richeſt and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſt happy who is moſt contented, when no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing is more certain
then it, the ſoule having no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaſures, no happineſſe, more properly her own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or more in
effect, then that of contentment.</p>
            <p>Hee that is poore in deſires is rich in content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent, one ſaith, who bridleth his
intemperate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſires, contendeth even with <hi>Jupiter</hi> himſelf in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elicitie, to him that
deſires but a little, a little <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eems much, and hee that covets no more then what hee hath, may be
ſaid to poſſeſſe all the World.</p>
            <p>But he that poſſeſſes abundance of theſe earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y happineſſes, and yet fears the
loſſe or want of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem, or out of a covetous, ambitious, or intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate voluptuous heart,
grieves becauſe hee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oyes not ſo much as he deſires, is as miſerable as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e that wants
them; thoſe who extend their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires beyond nature and moderation, letting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ooſe their
appetites, to follow vice and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluities, make ſuperfluous things neceſſary, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
ſouls ſlaves to their bodies, they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented. They would build houſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ble, and after of Iaſper and Porphyry. They would firſt poſſeſſe a Lordſhip, then
a Kingdome, after the World, which if they did, they would then think the World too litle, and
grieve becauſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:9564:15"/> they enjoy no more, no better Worlds, they a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> never ſatisfied. They would
have they know no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what, they are always reſtleſſe, ſtill deſire, trou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble, and perplex
themſelves till they bring them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelves into a fools Paradiſe.</p>
            <p>But this meane, for a man to enrich himſelf and to make himſelf happy and contented, by
deſiring little, according to nature, moderation and reaſon is very juſt. It is in every mans
power hee may finde it within himſelf, Nature hath ſo provided that in all things, ſo much as
ſufficeth, is at hand, and in our own power.</p>
            <p>A litle wee know of theſe earthly felicities is enough to ſuffice nature and to live well,
and wee may take as much felicity in ſufficiency as if we poſſeſſed all the riches,
honours and pleaſures in the world, which if we did, wee could enjoy the ſuperfluity, to wit,
that which is above ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency, onely by looking on, and contemplation, ſo may we while it is
anothers: what happineſſe is there on earth, which in our mindes by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation, we may not
enjoy?</p>
            <p>An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> commonly ſee, that poore men of low degree, are as contented as rich, noble and
voluptuous men, they are uſually more free from idleneſſe; ill paſſions, intemperance,
and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently from ſuch diſtempers as are incident therunto, and wee may obſerve, they
are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:9564:15"/> free, fearleſſe, ſecure, healthy, merry, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nted, happy men.</p>
            <p>Having therfore food and rayment, let us be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erwith contented, as wee are divinely exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d. And
concerning croſſes, want and troubles, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t ſuch conſiderations as follow (amongſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers
others which might be written) move us to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ontentation in all conditions.</p>
            <p>Croſſes want and troubles are common to all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en, oftentimes to the beſt men. It is a
ſigne of weakneſſe not to digeſt that with contentment, which cannot be avoided, which is
common to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll, to the beſt men, when we have ſo many and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch companions.</p>
            <p>Some croſſes and troubles are neceſſary, as Winter to Summer, elſe pleaſures and
proſperity would become dry, ſtale, weariſome, and cloy us: It is a mixture of croſſes
and adverſity, that makes proſperity and pleaſures moſt ſweet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us.</p>
            <p>We may convert our minds from thoſe things that offend us to thoſe which are pleaſing, and
afford us delectation. Though wee have ſome want and troubles, yet perchance we may enjoy many
pleaſures and felicities alſo, in ſo much that if wee be not too peeviſh and wayward, we
may drown our ſorows and croſſes in pleaſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and joy.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:9564:16"/>However, the worſt things have ſome mix<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture of comfort in them, and it is
certain, Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all croſſes and troubles will have an end, Cuſtom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Time will ſurely wear
them away. Cuſtom is a remedy againſt the moſt tedious and irkſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> troubles, even the Gally
ſlaves can ſing in thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſervitude, after they have been ſome time accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed therunto.
Time is the finiſher of all trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, perchance we have already well nigh forgo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all the
croſſes and ſorrows of our life time paſt and ſuch as wee do remember, wee rejoyce that
they are paſt and gone. And this good effect croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and adverſity alwayes leave behinde,
Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and proſperity after the ſame is paſt, is the ſweeter. Ioy and pleaſure after
ſorrow is a ſtrange enlightning to us, in ſuch ſort, as it ſhould ſeeme Nature hath
given ſorrow and troubles for the greater increaſe and ſervice of our plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and
delight.</p>
            <p>Foreſight, Expectation, Meditation, Wiſdome and Fortitude, are excellent Remedies againſt
croſſes and adverſitie. Let us therfore hereby en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devour to raiſe and quicken our ſpirits
above and beyond feare and adverſity. Contemning all the frowns and blows of the World, which do
ſcare and depreſſe onely weak and feeble ſpirits, and to ſettle our mindes in a contented
and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed tranquillity, which is a beautifull, ſweet, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:9564:16"/> pleaſant eſtate of the mind ſuch as neither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ood accidents, nor ill,
Proſperity nor adverſity an mend or depreſſe.</p>
            <p>Piety is yet a better remedy againſt croſſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd adverſity, and the beſt way to
contentment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd true happineſſe. To conſider that the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God our loving Father doth by
his moſt wiſe, juſt, loving and good Providence order and guide all things, is enough to make
us ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y contented in all conditions. It is a ſafe and a happy way to apply our wils to his
will. It is effeminacy and daſtardlines to complain againſt God; and greatly addes to our
miſery. It is mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimity and courage to yield to him. It is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect freedome and
happineſſe to obey God. Hee that follows his Captains commands through ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity and
dangers, aſwell as proſperity ſhall be greatly rewarded. The good Souldiers of our heavenly
Captain ſhall be crowned with eternal glory and triumph.</p>
            <p>Let us then doe our beſt endevours in all good wayes for the attainment of earthly
Happineſſe, and depend on the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the Almightie for ſucceſſe, truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him
in all things, caſting all our care upon him, who truly careth for ſuch as rely on him, and
truly knows what is beſt for us: ſo may
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:9564:17"/> we be aſſured that in what eſtate ſoever wee be in, the ſame is
beſt for us, and that all things ſhall convert to our happineſſe, let the World toſſe
and vary it ſelf how it liſt, we ſhall ever remayn ſafe and happy. Even croſſes,
loſſes, want and all afflictions ſhall then increaſe our happineſſe, for why,</p>
            <p>Firſt, we ſhall be delivered out of all afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>Many are the troubles of the
righteous, ſaith King David</hi> (though often more are the troubles of the unrighteous) but the
Lord, ſaith he, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers the righteous) out of all. <hi>And they that ſow in tears, ſhall
reap in joy:</hi> Oftentimes they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in this life, certainly in heaven. How pleaſant
will heaven be eternally to ſuch as have been here in want and afflicted for a time? a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in
compariſon.</p>
            <p>Secondly, wee may have joy in all croſſes and afflictions. Our Saviour ſaith, <hi>In the
world yee ſhall have afflictions, but in mee you ſhall rejoyce, and your joy ſhall no man
take from you. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the righteous doth ariſe in trouble joy, in darknes light,</hi> ſaith
King <hi>David,</hi> afflictions and want do often ſtirre up and quicken good ſoules to look
and ſee farre into heaven, poſſeſſing themſelves, with moſt ſweet and heavenly joys
and conſolations, <hi>I do abound with all joy, ſaith Saint</hi> Paul, <hi>in the midſt of
tribulation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:9564:17"/>Thirdly, the ſame ſhall turn to our good, <hi>All <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ings worke to the good
of them that love God,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> Afflictions take from us all baſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>are and
effeminacie, they are purgations to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enſe us, and bridles to with-hold us from evils. They are
ſpurs to excite us to all goodneſſe, <hi>It is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ood for me, ſaith King</hi> David, <hi>that
I have been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fflicted.</hi> Troubles, want, and croſſes make us wiſer, more circumſpect,
reſolute and couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. The ſame tryes, exerciſes, increaſes, quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens, and refines all
heavenly grace in us, <hi>Your light afflictions which are but for a moment, ſaith Saint</hi>
Paul, <hi>ſhall work in you an eternall waight of glory.</hi> This glory if wee could truly think
of, though we ſhould ſuffer all the miſeries on earth, yet ſhould wee greatly rejoyce, and
glory to think, at what an eaſie rate we ſhould gain ſuch eternall happineſſe.</p>
            <p>Why then ſhould we not be ſweetly conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in all conditions, ſith there may be ſuch
hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe in loſſes, croſſes, want and afflictions, and what better happineſſe
can wee learn then to be contented, and ſweetly pleaſed in all eſtates and occurrences, and
ſo to enjoy theſe earthly hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſes, with a contented, fearleſſe, free and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py
minde?</p>
            <p>Such men therfore as are well perſwaded of the goodneſſe and fitneſſe of their
condition
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:9564:18"/> whatſoever it be, and their mindes ſetled in a free, fearleſſe and
contented eſtate, are to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed happy men, and no men living are able to enjoy more true
pleaſure and happineſſe on earth then ſuch men.</p>
            <p>So that whether we loſe, want, have ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy or abundance, Let us make a good uſe
therof, be contented with, and rejoyce in all things.</p>
            <div type="abstract">
               <head>The abſtract of the ſecond SECTION.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe way in earthly things, true joy to finde,</l>
                  <l>Is to enjoy them with contented minde,</l>
                  <l>He is the richeſt and moſt happy man,</l>
                  <l>Who (being moderate in deſires) can</l>
                  <l>Content himſelf, and ſweetly pleaſed bee</l>
                  <l>In all eſtates, conditions, each degree.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Who covets nought, doth all the world poſſeſſe,</l>
                  <l>And ſure he may contend in happineſſe</l>
                  <l>With <hi>love</hi> himſelf, but he that fears the loſſe</l>
                  <l>Of earthly things, and grieves at every croſſe,</l>
                  <l>Or letting looſe his appetite, doth extend</l>
                  <l>His vitious deſires beyond the end</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:9564:18"/>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> moderation and of reaſon, ſure</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e is not happy, but he ſhall endure</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> reſtleſſe diſcontent; he fain would be</l>
                  <l>A Lord, a King, an Emperour, then he,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he World would have, nay more, he knows not what</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ouſes of Jasper, neither this, nor that</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an pleaſe his minde, ſurely he is not wiſe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e brings himſelf into Fools Paradiſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut nature hath provided for us ſo</l>
                  <l>As every man may be content. We know</l>
                  <l>A litle is ſufficient to ſuffice</l>
                  <l>Nature it ſelf. And he thats truly wiſe</l>
                  <l>Within himſelf can true contentment finde,</l>
                  <l>He enjoys even all the world within his minde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Give me the ſilent ſhade, the quiet life,</l>
                  <l>The happy Country, free from Cities ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>The buſh where under <hi>Tityrus</hi> did ſing,</l>
                  <l>And no more wealth then may contentment bring,</l>
                  <l>He bring the choiceſt Nymphs into my Cell,</l>
                  <l>The Muſes and the Graces there ſhall dwell.</l>
                  <l>I will endevour, ſweeteſt joys to finde,</l>
                  <l>To enjoy both earth and heaven in my minde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>'Tis ſure a happy ſtate and free from ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>To live a ſtill, poor, and contented life,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:9564:19"/>We often ſee that poore deſpiſed men</l>
                  <l>Are healthy, merry, happy, Let us then</l>
                  <l>In all estates, ever contented be,</l>
                  <l>Yea, even in croſſes, troubles, miſerie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Croſſes and troubles are to all men common</l>
                  <l>Let us not grieve too much for that which no m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Living is free from, and we know indeed</l>
                  <l>Some croſſes neceſſary are, we need</l>
                  <l>A mixture, pleaſures elſe were bitter,</l>
                  <l>Stale, &amp; would cloy us, croſſes make them ſweete</l>
                  <l>And though we have ſome troubles, yet there be</l>
                  <l>A thouſand pleaſures in the world, which we</l>
                  <l>May ſtill enjoy, ſo as perchance we may</l>
                  <l>Drown all our griefs in pleaſantneſſe and j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y:</l>
                  <l>And though our troubles ſhould be very bitter,</l>
                  <l>Yet being paſt, pleaſure will then be ſweeter.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Wiſdome and fortitude may raiſe our minde</l>
                  <l>To ſuch a noble temper, we may finde</l>
                  <l>Such peace and courage in us as we dare</l>
                  <l>Contemne the World when't frowns, and no whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> fear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Its blows, which onely feeble minds depreſſe</l>
                  <l>And heerby crown our ſelves with happineſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But yet the ſureſt and beſt remedy,</l>
                  <l>Againſt all croſſes and adverſity,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:9564:19"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o advance our mindes to pietie,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s indeed true magnanimity</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> yield to God, ſuch are the happieſt men</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o truſt in him in all things. Let us then</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> all good ways endevour to attain</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rreſtriall happineſſe. Concerning gain</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t us on him, who cares for us, depend,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d always what is beſt for us doth ſend.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> may we happy be and reſt ſecure</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> all conditions; we may now be ſure</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat even croſſes, want and miſery,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hall now convert to our felicity.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e ſhall from all afflictions be releaſt</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd joy will be moſt ſweet when ſorrow's paſt</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ow pleaſant will heaven be eternally,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o ſuch as heere have ſuffered miſery?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nto the righteous often doth ariſe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> trouble joy, in darkneſſe to their eyes</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oth heavenly light appeare, ſo as we may</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> trouble ſee and taſte of heavenly joy.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fflictions take from us effeminacie</l>
                  <l>And all baſe feare addes magnanimitie,</l>
                  <l>Wiſdome and goodneſſe in us, quickens, tries</l>
                  <l>All heavenly grace; and in ſuch exerciſe</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:9564:20"/>Refines and purifies the ſame, that even,</l>
                  <l>Our joy ſhall be therby, increaſt in heaven.</l>
                  <l>This heavenly joy and glory if we could</l>
                  <l>But truly think and taſt therof, we ſhould</l>
                  <l>Though all earths miſeries were in the way,</l>
                  <l>Go through them all, with ſweet and pleaſant</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Since that ſuch joy, ſuch happineſſe may be</l>
                  <l>In croſſes, loſſes, want and miſery</l>
                  <l>Let us in all conditions, ſweetly reſt</l>
                  <l>Contented, ſo ſhall we be ever bleſt.</l>
                  <l>None can enjoy more earthly pleaſure then</l>
                  <l>Such as be fearleſſe, free, contented men.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So whether want or have, or loſe, or gain,</l>
                  <l>We always happy, joyfull, may remayn.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="section">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:9564:20"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The third Section.</hi> We muſt enjoy earthly happineſſe in the good uſe
therof.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O the knowledge of &amp; contentment in the felicities of the earth, we muſt adde a third
intention, to wit, good uſe therof, if wee mean to be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> herein.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o much therfore as wee do poſſeſſe, and may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oy of theſe earthly happineſſes, let
us uſe the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e well, and ſo let us enjoy them freely and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erfully, without this good uſe, and
if inſtead <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r of we abuſe them, what can wee expect but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elicity and miſery therin, even in
this world, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all abuſes (that is all immoderate and vitious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ires, intentions and ill
uſes therof) are ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es to health, peace and happines. A multitude <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> paſſions,
perturbations, cares, fears, griefs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, diſeaſes, diſtempers and miſeries are inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt to
all vices, to all abuſes, and no men even
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:9564:21"/> on earth, live more unhappily, more miſerab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> then abuſive vitious men.</p>
            <p>While therefore wee view the pleaſantne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> number, variety, excellency, and happy effects
terreſtriall felicities, wee are by all means to very carefull that in the uſe and enjoyance
th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of we exceed not moderation; and plunge o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſelves into the dangers and abuſes therof, and
inſtead of happines therin, cauſe to our ſelv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> much grief and miſery. For why,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Satan is very buſie with theſe earth pleaſures and felicities, prompting us to
abuſe and ſo endevouring by their ill uſe to ſteal aw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> our hearts from all heavenly
graces, and ſo fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God himſelf, hee offers us a terreſtriall Paradi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> alſo, and cryes,
<hi>All this will I give thee, if the wilt fall down and worſhip me.</hi> But he doth no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tably
cozen and mock us, hee deals with us as h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> did with <hi>Adam,</hi> though he offers us Paradiſe,
te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> us we ſhall be as Gods, &amp;c. yet hee gives us b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> an Apple, and ſuch an Apple as the
eating the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of will bereave us of all good, fill us with all evill and cauſe us to be driven out
of the Paradiſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all felicities, into a world of miſerie. His offer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and gifts are like that
gay painted Box of <hi>Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dora,</hi> ſtuffed with all manner of evils and miſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ries, if wee
could ſee the evill and miſery of the condition, we ſhould think it infinitely too great
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:9564:21"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te to buy his painted proffers, yet theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hly things are ſometimes his
principall baits <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>atch fools withall, wherby he carries them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll wickednes, I mean ſuch fools as
King <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſpeaks of, and King <hi>Solomon, Fools are we by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on of our
tranſgreſſions,</hi> Let us take heed we not into his unhappy miſerable fooles Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Alſo the ſtrong torrent of our ſenſuall corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns being once ſet a running, after
vice and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ckednes, will often break down the banks of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>deration and ſtint; and (if wee be not
very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tchfull and cautelous) flow to all manner of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſe and diſſoluteneſſe, for
wickednes and vice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ery deceitfull, and with its painted vanities <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d ſugred baits of ſeeming
pleaſure, draws and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>res our ſenſuall appetites, ſometimes una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>res, beyond the
bound-marks of Reaſon and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mperance, and ſo blinds us, as that we are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n perſwaded, that
we are about the buſineſſe, health, and moderate recreation, when indeed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e are canvaſing
for intemperance, and our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndes even ready to be drawne away to wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dnes and impiety. And therfore
we had need <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be carefull and cautelous.</p>
            <p>The World alſo, even theſe earthly felicities <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> themſelves, have many dangerous
tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ons to vice and wickednes, and conſequently
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:9564:22"/> to hinder the happines thereof, and to make miſerable therin, even on
earth.</p>
            <p>The riches of the World (being an huge hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and many benefits ſpringing from the good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
therof) will if we take not heed draw our hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to covetouſnes, and covetouſnes having once
e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tred our ſouls, will poſſeſſe us with a baſe ſord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> deſire of riches, and wee
ſhall become thereb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> unjuſt, deceitfull, pinching, niggardly, and full <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> unworthy
conditions. Alwayes poſſeſt wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cares, feares, ſuſpitions and diſcontents;
eſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cially at every loſſe or croſſe, though of ſmal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> value.</p>
            <p>Honour alſo having a bright luſtre, ſhining t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the World, and being much deſired of
great ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rits, doth tempt us to that towring and topleſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vice, ambition poſſeſſing
us with a ravenous dry unſatiable thirſt therof, making us to become ful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of vain plots, fears
&amp; perplexities, and exceeding deſperate and melancholy at every accident <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thwarting our
deſires therin.</p>
            <p>And pleaſures alſo with their painted and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gred baits allure us, and if we beware not
will cauſe us to fall into unlawful luſts, intemperance, and all manner of prodigalities, which
are at their beſt but fugitive follies, and their end melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and miſery, and ſo to
plunge our ſelves into a multitude of griefs, aches, diſeaſes, paſſions, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbations
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:9564:22"/> and miſeries, which are incident to temperance, Idleneſſe, Luſt, Riot,
and all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oderate and diſſolute uſe of Pleaſures.</p>
            <p>So that it appeares, vice and wickedneſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hough the ſame have an outward ſhew of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>auty
yet) is inwardly like a painted ſepulture, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> horrid, foule, and ugly, full of baſe
deſires, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>amefull actions, dangers, vanities, impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ents, anguiſh, diſtempers,
paſſions, perturbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s and miſeries, even in this life, the ſame at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt is ſurely
but a Fools Paradiſe.</p>
            <p>To the intent therfore that we may be happy reſpect of theſe earthly Felicities, let us by
all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eans endevour to avoid the dangers and abuſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erof, all unlawfull, immoderate and evill
deſires <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d uſes therof.</p>
            <p>And in all reſpects let us endevour to uſe the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me wel. The good uſe of earthly felicities
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſteth in three points. The firſt concerning our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lves, the ſecond, others. The third,
and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Gods Glory, to which the two former are ſo to be directed.</p>
            <p>Firſt, concerning our ſelves, Temperance is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he razor and the rule of enjoying earthly
Felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, the razor to cut off all abuſes, all ſtrange and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itious ſuperfluities, and the
rule of that which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> good and neceſſary, keeping us alwayes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the precincts of
reaſon, and vertue. Let us ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore in the uſe and enjoyance of earthly pleaſures
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:9564:23"/> and Felicities, ſtill obſerve a due moderation, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> order, in reſpect of
matter, meaſure, time, man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner and all occaſions, in ſuch ſort as the ſame ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> beſt
tend to our well being, as to the preſervati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of nature. The maintenance of our bodies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
mindes in due temper and vigour, ſo as we ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be able to perform all the duties and actions
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> our life, with alacrity, cheerfulnes and pleaſant<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>There are no men in the world that live mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pleaſantly, healthfully, proſperouſly, and in
all re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpects happily then the moderate vertuous man for by reaſon of his temperance in the
deſires and in the uſe of theſe earthly Felicities, his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy commonly becomes free and cleer
from cru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dities, rheumes, noyſomnes, ill diſeaſes, and di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtempers, and ſo moſt
healthy, agill, lightſome and expedite to all the motions appertaining therunto, his minde alſo
thereby becomes fre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from ſloth, dulnes, evill paſſions, and perturbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, his affections
well tempered, and his whole ſoul apt, perſpicuous, free, and cheerful in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of
all the actions and exerciſes therof. His whole life reſembles a fair, bright and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant
day, wherin are no clouds, no tempeſt, but all fairnes, ſerenity and peace, hee ſeems to go
to heaven, treading on Roſes.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in reſpect of others, we ought ſo to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:9564:23"/> uſe and enjoy earthly happines, as the ſame may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e without offence,
ſcandall, damage, and preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of another. The vertue of Iuſtice ought to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e our rule herein.
Charity and liberality ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e alſo exerciſed hereby. Let us therfore doe no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arme but all
the good herein, that conveniently we may to our Family, Friends, Kindred, Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, as alſo
in general to the Church and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth.</p>
            <p>No man liveth more unworthily, then he that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iveth meerly for himſelf, but hee that uſeth
his time, his goods, and his endevours for the good of others alſo, liveth moſt worthily and
hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably.</p>
            <p>But thirdly, all our endevours, indeed all our actions, pleaſures and enjoyances ought to be
directed to this point, to wit, Gods glory. Let us always remember Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> rule,
<hi>Whatſoever yee do, let all be done to the praiſe and glorie of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let theſe earthly pleaſures and Felicities ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite and encourage us to thankfulnes, to all
duties of vertue and piety, to look higher to their foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, to God himſelf, to heaven, to love
and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in him, to contemplate his infinite good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, love, beauty, ſweetnes, glory, and
excellency. And ſo to enjoy theſe earthly Felicities with a heavenly minde, and by theſe
alſo to ſpie and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:9564:24"/> a Paradiſe of heavenly delights on earth. Of all which I intend to write
more largely and particularly in the laſt Section.</p>
            <p>So then if wee can thus uſe them, let us freely enjoy them in their greateſt excellency,
pleaſure and happines.</p>
            <div type="abstract">
               <head>The abſtract of the third SECTION.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>HE that on earth, will happy be, muſt uſe</l>
                  <l>Terreſtriall happineſſe without abuſe,</l>
                  <l>For all abuſes, all intemperate</l>
                  <l>Deſires, are enemies to a happy State,</l>
                  <l>A multitude of aches, griefs and cares,</l>
                  <l>Diſtempers, paſſions, perturbations, fears,</l>
                  <l>Anguiſh, and miſeries are incident</l>
                  <l>To vitious men, they ſeldome are content,</l>
                  <l>Though vice ſeem pleaſant, yet aſſuredly</l>
                  <l>Sorrow ſhall follow all impiety.</l>
                  <l>And therfore vitious men, as moſt unwiſe,</l>
                  <l>Do alſo run into Fools Paradiſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>There is none living in the World that can</l>
                  <l>Live ſo contented as the vertuous man,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:9564:24"/>He lives moſt healthy, happy, free, ſecure,</l>
                  <l>Pleaſantly cheerfull, always being ſure,</l>
                  <l>The treaſures, riches, pleaſures of his minde,</l>
                  <l>Shall ever laſt, his happy ſoul doth finde</l>
                  <l>A free delight in all things, and the way</l>
                  <l>To heaven he rides as in a Summers day.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let vertue rule us then, in earthly pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>Let temperance in all things, teach us meaſure,</l>
                  <l>So let us then, a mean in all things uſe,</l>
                  <l>In matter, meaſure, time, without abuſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let juſtice alſo, guide us in this way,</l>
                  <l>Lets do no harm, but all the good we may.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Remembring always in all things to give</l>
                  <l>Him glory who gives theſe, by whom we live,</l>
                  <l>And let theſe earthly pleaſures us excite</l>
                  <l>To all good actions, alſo move, invite</l>
                  <l>And quicken our dull mindes themſelves to raiſe</l>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p higher to their fountaine. And rejoyce</l>
                  <l>In him, with pure, divine and heartie love</l>
                  <l>And ſo by looking up to heaven above</l>
                  <l>From whence theſe lower joys do ſpring, we may</l>
                  <l>A heavenly Paradiſe likewiſe enjoy</l>
                  <l>Of ſweet delights on earth, ſo may we finde</l>
                  <l>The joys of earth and heaven in our minde.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="section">
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:9564:25"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The fourth Section.</hi> We may enjoy earthly happineſſe freely, and
cheerfully.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>Nowing earthly happines, being contented in all conditions, in reſpect thereof, and uſing
the ſame well, we may now in ſuch knowledge, contentment, and good uſe enjoy the ſame
freely and cheerfully, even in its greateſt excellency, pleaſure and happineſſe.</p>
            <p>Which to the intent we may, we muſt alſo ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh out of our mindes, all idle,
ſuperſtitious, er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronious opinions, concerning the ſame.</p>
            <p>Certai ly, if we would adviſedly think and be perſwaded as the truth is, that Vertue and
Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is a furtherance to the enjoying of earthly happines, rather then a hinderance therin,
and that the enjoying of the Felicities of the earth freely, is not contrary to Vertue, Religion,
and heavenly happineſſe, nor any hinderance if not
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:9564:25"/> abuſed, but in the good uſe and enjoyance ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, rather a furtherance
therunto (all which in due place I ſhall further endevour to ſhew) wee ſhould be more
carefull &amp; diligent in ſeeking the felicities both of earth and heaven.</p>
            <p>Yet ſee thoſe common and main errors of the World in this kinde, multitudes of men
concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that Religion doth debarre them from the enjoying of earthly Felicities, to which they
are naturally ſtrongly inclined, will not ſearch into the happy ways of Religion and Piety,
which leadeth to eternall happineſſe.</p>
            <p>And many men knowing the vanities; dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and impediments of theſe earthly Felicities, do
become in their carriage and writings too auſtere, Stoicall, Monkiſh and rigid in the
en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyance of the ſame.</p>
            <p>There are many indeed (who would ſeem) to be men of notable underſtanding, doe ſtudy to
contemne and tread underfoot all ſorts of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and care of the body, retyring the
ſpirit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it ſelf, not having any commerce with the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but elevating it ſelfe to high
things, and ſo would ſeem to ſlide through this life inſenſibly, neither taſting, not
attending it, ſuſpecting not onely recreations and paſtimes, but alſo neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
which God hath ſeaſoned with ſome plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. They come unwillingly into places of law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,

<pb n="32" facs="tcp:9564:26"/> honeſt, and harmleſſe pleaſures, &amp; hold their breath till they are
gone, as if they were in place<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of infection, they feare to uſe earthly pleaſures (though well)
and ſo to enjoy them becauſe they ſee ſome vanities and danger, in them, ſo as the earth,
yea, even their life is burthenſome and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive to them, and they ſeeme to be willing to
die before their time.</p>
            <p>It is moſt certain indeed, that there are many vanities, dangers, &amp; impediments in theſe
earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Felicities, but this hinders not, but wee may enjoy them in their good uſe freely and
cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, as I ſhall endevour to ſhew plainly, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the objections to the contrary,
in the enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sections: And it is alſo moſt certain, that moderate due &amp; convenient
faſting, abſtinence, and forbearance of earthly pleaſures, retyred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, divine
melancholy and ſolitarineſſe, as I may call it, heavenly contemplation, extaſies and the
like, addes ſprightfulneſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd heavenly wings to our ſouls, ſo as therby wee become the
more Angell like, apt and prepared to receive, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and enjoy all divine Graces, all heavenly
joys &amp; conſolations, even to elevate our ſouls to the heavenly Paradiſe, and to enjoy God
himſelf and heavenly delights in ſome degree on earth. But the ſame ought to be done duly and
conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently, as I intend to ſhew in the ſeventh Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, not hindring the free and cheerfull
enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ance
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:9564:26"/> of earthly happineſſe at due and convenient times alſo, in the good
uſe therof, which ſo may and ought to be enjoyed freely and cheerfully.</p>
            <p>And it is alſo certain, that by an immoderate melancholy, and overnice and ſlaviſh
forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of convenient, good, harmleſſe pleaſures, the ſpirit may ſomtimes become
ſingular, vain-glorious, curious, and wandring from harmleſſe and lawfull wayes. So while
theſe men would ſeem to live after a ſtrange manner, wholly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove themſelves: By not
endevouring to play the parts of men, aſwell as of Angels, they ſomtimes proceed to conceive
and maintaine prodigious Paradoxes, and erroneous fancies.</p>
            <p>But wee are to know, that while wee are in this life, It is very fair, good, lawfull, and
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, for us to learn well, to play the parts of a Man; yea, it is a divine knowledge in a
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and vertuous manner, rightly and duly to governe, uſe and enjoy, both the pleaſures
of the minde and of the body alſo, and not to renounce the meaneſt of them, but in their good
uſe freely to enjoy them, to which Nature provokes us, Reaſon alſo excites us, yea, Religion
and God himſelf exhorts us. All which I ſhall endevour to ſhew as plainly as I may.</p>
            <p>We muſt conſider, wee have bodies aſwell as ſouls, which require due refreſhments,
recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:9564:27"/> and pleaſures, to which every man findeth in himſelf a naturall appetite
and deſire, yea, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity compels us therunto, wee could not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt nor live
without theſe. And Nature willeth very wiſely, that theſe actions which it hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned us
for our neceſſity, be alſo delightfull, inviting us therunto not onely by appetite, but by
reaſon.</p>
            <p>What greater folly is there, and more againſt reaſon aſwell as nature, to account our
actions vitious, becauſe they are naturall, unworthy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe neceſſary, and pleaſant.
It is indeed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Iuſtice, to be too defective, ſtoicall and rigid on the one ſide.
As to be too exceſſive and ſuperfluous on the other. So that as wee ought not to take ſuch
pleaſure in earthly things as to prejudice the health and ſafety of our bodies and mindes by
exceſſe and abuſes, ſo wee ought not alſo to take ſo little pleaſure therin, as to
hinder the welfare therof through defect.</p>
            <p>In ſuch ſort, as wee muſt not diſallow and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove naturall and convenient pleaſures,
as wee do thoſe which are impious, vitious, and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous, but rather greatly commend the
ſame, for as much as that reaſonable meane may be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved therin, which is good and
commendable in all things. And ſo without queſtion that delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which proceedeth from the
temperate and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:9564:27"/> good uſe of pleaſures is to be enjoy'd freely and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heerfully.</p>
            <p>And it is alſo reaſon, that the minde ſhould partake with the body of ſuch naturall
pleaſures which are juſt, good, and convenient Theſe two, the body and the minde, are as it
were married together, it is againſt reaſon, not well done to divide and ſeparate this
naturall conjunction, but rather wee ſhould renew the ſame by mutuall offices.</p>
            <p>The Spirit ought to quicken and revive the dull, heavy body. The body alſo ſhould ſtay and
allay that ſtrange, unnaturall, prodigious, proud, extravagant lightneſſe of the ſpirit.
The Spirit ſhould aſſiſt and favour the body, as the husband, the wife. And not reject it
nor hate it. It ſhould not abandon the body, and refuſe the naturall pleaſures therof, which
are due, convenient, juſt, lawfull, and moderate, ſuch as befits the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage that is between
them. It ſeemeth unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, Preſumption, Pride and Folly ſo to do, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to right and
reaſon; It ſhould a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her in all caſes aſſiſt the body to mayntaine it alwayes in due
order.</p>
            <p>And as Nature and Reaſon, ſo alſo Religion commendeth, yea, willeth and commandeth the
enjoyment of earthly happineſſe, within the bounds of Temperance and Vertue. It is true
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:9564:28"/> indeed, Religion exhorts and commands us to avoid intemperance and abuſes
herein, and to uſe them well. But herein it doth greatly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe our happineſſe even on
earth, for as hath been ſhewed, a multitude of reſtleſſe deſires, cares, feares,
diſtempers, anguiſh and miſeries proceed from all vice and impiety even in this World. And no
men on earth live more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly, healthfully, proſperouſly, and happily then the
contented, temperate, vertuous, graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man. So that Religion greatly addes to our free enjoyance
of Terreſtriall happineſſe in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting us to avoid the abuſes therof, and to uſe the
ſame well. And in ſuch good uſe, it commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, willeth and commandeth the enjoyance therof
freely and cheerfully. And greatly bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth ſuch as forbid and teach the contrary. To inſtance
in ſome places of the ſacred Scriptures.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou ſhalt rejoyce in every good thing which the Lord thy God hath given thee, Thou and
the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite and the ſtranger that is among you,</hi> Deut. 26.11. <hi>Becauſe the Lord thy God
ſhall bleſſe thee in all thy increaſe, and in all the work of thy hands, therfore thou
ſhalt ſurely rejoyce</hi> Deut. 16.5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Behold, that which I have ſeene, (ſaith the Preacher) It is good and comely for a man to
eat and to drink, and to enjoy the good of all his labour, that he taketh under the Sun all the
days of his life, which God giveth him, for it is his portion. Every
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:9564:28"/> man alſo to whom God hath given riches and wealth, and hath given him power
to eate thereof, and to take his portion, and to rejoyce in his labour, This is the gift of God, He
ſhall not much remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the days of his life, becauſe God anſwereth him in the joy of his
heart,</hi> Eccles. 5.18, 19, 20.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rejoyce in the wife of thy youth, Let her be unto thee as the pleaſant Hind &amp; loving
Roe, &amp; rejoyce in her love continually, ſaith Solomon,</hi> Pro. 5.17.</p>
            <p>Now the Spirit ſpeaketh expreſly, ſaith Saint <hi>Paul, That in the latter times, ſome
ſhall depart from the faith, giving heed to ſeducing ſpirits, and doctrines of Devils,
ſpeaking lyes in hypocriſie, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their conſciences feared with a hot iron, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding to
marry, and commanding to abſtain from meats, which God hath created to be received with
thanksgiving of them which believe and know the truth, for every creature if God is good, and
no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be refuſed of it be received with thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, for it is ſanctified by the Word
of God and Prayer.</hi> 1 Tim. 4.2, 3, 4, 5.</p>
            <p>By theſe few inſtances (amongſt divers others which might be added) it appeares that we
may freely and cheerfully enjoy theſe earthly happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and that ſuch as forbid or deny
the ſame are greatly to be blamed. The rather becauſe as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſignifieth in
the forenamed place to <hi>Timothy, That God hath created them to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:9564:29"/> with thanksgiving of them which believe and know the truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God himſelf is the Author of theſe. <hi>Riches and honour come from God</hi> (ſaith King
<hi>Solomon) and the bleſſing of the Lord maketh rich. He created,</hi> ſaith <hi>Moſes,
the Paradiſe of pleaſure, wherin hee planted man. They are Gods gifts,</hi> ſaith the Wife
man, <hi>and ordained of him,</hi> (which appears alſo by their variety and pleaſantneſſe)
<hi>not only for neceſſitie but for lawful and moderate delight, Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles.</hi> 5.18, 19. And
therfore if well uſed are to be eſteemed as his gifts and bleſſings.</p>
            <p>Alſo they may ſerve to many excellent uſes, as hath been ſaid in the former Section,
even to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in us heavenly joy and happineſſe alſo, of which I intend to write in the
laſt Section.</p>
            <p>And therfore in all theſe reſpects it appeares, That ſuch as uſe theſe terreſtriall
Felicities with moderate delectation, to the glory of God, and ſo to good ends, are better to be
reputed, then ſuch as unduly, inconſideratly and raſhly, neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect and refuſe ſo great
good which God loving<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and freely offers to our acceptance.</p>
            <p>Wherefore Monks, Anchorites, Carthuſian Fryers, and others of the rigid and Stoicall ſort of
people are in a great error, who ſuperſtitiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly refuſe and neglect Riches, Honours,
Mariage, Fleſh, Wine, moderate and lawfull Recreations
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:9564:29"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n their good uſe. It ſeems they think themſelves wiſer in refuſing,
then their Creator is in offering <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o great benefits.</p>
            <p>This ſuperſtitious opinion is moſt commonly found in diſcontented brain-ſicke men;
Surely they are injurious, to reaſon, unjuſtly depriving themſelves of the good enjoyance of
much hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, yea, to Religion and God himſelfe, very much detracting from his
goodneſſe, and moſt free love and kindneſſe.</p>
            <p>From whence ſhould this opinion and beliefe ſpring, that God taketh pleaſure in the
refuſall &amp; neglect of the good uſe and enjoyance of his creatures, which hee freely
commends, exhorts, and offers to our acceptance. But the wiſer Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers and Chriſtians
have beene and are of another opinion; as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 1
<hi>Tim.</hi> 4. The practice alſo of our Saviour, Who ſaith of himſelfe, <hi>The Sonne of
man came eating and drinking, &amp;c. Matth</hi> 11. Of the Chriſtians in the Primitive Church.
<hi>Who did eat their meat together with gladneſſe and ſingleneſſe of heart, Acts</hi>
2.46. Of thoſe which reſorted to the feaſts of Charity mentioned. <hi>Iude</hi> 12. which are
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded to be certain Banquets which the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians kept altogether, and of divers other in
all ages. Do ſhew that this opinion of the free and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:9564:30"/> cheerfull enjoyance of earthly happineſſe in the moderate and good uſe
therof ought to be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced. The objections to the contrary, I ſhall endevour to anſwer in the
following Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</p>
            <p>So that if we will be ruled by Nature, Reaſon, Religion, by God himſelf, if wee will follow
the opinion of the wiſer Chriſtians. The practice of our Saviour, and of thoſe Chriſtians
in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church and others in all Ages, if we can uſe theſe earthly Felicities with
Temperance, to the glory of God, wee may ſurely enjoy them in ſuch good uſe freely and
cheerfully.</p>
            <p>Let us then enjoy God in all things, and all things in him, and to his glory.</p>
            <div type="abstract">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:9564:30"/>
               <head>The abſtract of the fourth SECTION.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THat we in Earths delights, free joy may finde,</l>
                  <l>Lets baniſh Superſtition from our minde.</l>
                  <l>Moſt certainly, if we could truly ſee</l>
                  <l>Religious excellencie, we ſhould be</l>
                  <l>Enamour'd with its beauty preſently</l>
                  <l>However ſome do think that rigidly,</l>
                  <l>The ſame doth hinder earths felicity,</l>
                  <l>And therfore too too ſuperſtitiouſly</l>
                  <l>Refuſe the ſame, ſo making others feare</l>
                  <l>To tread theſe divine paths, conceiting there</l>
                  <l>Is nought but rigid ſolitarineſſe</l>
                  <l>Debarring them, from earthly happineſſe</l>
                  <l>Wheras indeed, the ſame doth much increaſe</l>
                  <l>Terreſtriall joys, externall happineſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Theſe men would ſeeme to be exceeding wiſe</l>
                  <l>In ſtudying altogether to deſpiſe</l>
                  <l>All earthly pleaſures, inſomuch they feare</l>
                  <l>To ſee or taſte therof, as if they were</l>
                  <l>Infectious, in their good and harmleſſe uſe</l>
                  <l>And ſo becauſe of dangers in abuſe</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:9564:31"/>They weakly fear to enjoy them, Thus they finde</l>
                  <l>The world a grief, a burthen to their minde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Wheras in truth, we ought without abuſe</l>
                  <l>To enjoy earth happineſſe, in its good uſe</l>
                  <l>Freely, to which Nature greatly excites us</l>
                  <l>And reaſon alſo liberally invites us.</l>
                  <l>Juſtice and Temperance d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> aſwell condemne,</l>
                  <l>Stupidity and fayling in extreme</l>
                  <l>As the other way, intemperance in exceſſe,</l>
                  <l>Both hindering true delight and happineſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Religion alſo doth commend the joy.</l>
                  <l>Which in the temperate uſe therof we may</l>
                  <l>Receive therin, it bids us freely take</l>
                  <l>Thoſe pleaſures which were onely for our ſake</l>
                  <l>Created, and which God doth freely give</l>
                  <l>For our neceſſities while here we live</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And moderate delectation, Let us then</l>
                  <l>Freely enjoy the ſame, ſurely ſuch men</l>
                  <l>As will refuſe ſuch joy, ſo great a bliſſe</l>
                  <l>As heaven doth offer, greatly do amiſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But Lord, do thou our mindes ſo guide, ſo raiſe,</l>
                  <l>That we all things in thee, and to thy praiſe</l>
                  <l>May ſtill enjoy, and alſo that we may</l>
                  <l>Thy ſelf in all things, evermore enjoy.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="section">
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:9564:31"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The fifth Section.</hi> Wee may enjoy earthly Felicities, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their
vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He reaſons why many men do ſo much condemne the free and cheerfull enjoyance of earthly
happineſſes, are becauſe of their vanities, dangers, impediments and the like.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall now endevour to ſhew, that wee may and ought to enjoy them freely and
cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully notwithſtanding theſe; And firſt in this Section, Notwithſtanding their
vanities. Thoſe that would mayntain the contrary, do worthily and truly tell us, That earthly
Riches, Honours, and Pleaſures are vain, ſhort, uncertain, and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:9564:32"/> And that in compariſon of eternall an heavenly Felicities, they are not
worthy to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> eſteemed, but rather to be deſpiſed.</p>
            <p>It is moſt certaine indeed, that thoſe ſoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which do often contemplate the heavenly glor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
and are truly raiſed to the knowledge of divin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> things, are elevated above all pleaſures and
Feli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cities of the earth, in as much as Eternity is abov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> time, and infinite Felicities above
vanities. An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in theſe thoughts they are often ſo raiſed abov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> themſelves, that if they
were capable of vaniti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they woud not know themſelves, while thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſouls are thus contemplating
on the treaſures, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> glory, and the delights of heaven.</p>
            <p>So as they do in part taſte before hand of the ſweetneſſe of thoſe Felicities which
they hope to receive at the end of their life; which makes them very generouſly to tread under
foot, all the pleaſures and greatneſſes of the earth, while their ſouls are in ſuch
contemplations, directing their aymes to heaven.</p>
            <p>And it is alſo moſt true that the Felicities of the earth are not worthy to be compared with
thoſe of heaven either in worth, or duration of time, they are altogether vain, even as nothing
in ſuch compariſon.</p>
            <p>Yet notwithſtanding in reſpect of our nature, infirmities, weakneſſes, and
neceſſities, And in
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:9564:32"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſpect, of themſelves alſo without ſuch compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>on. They are to be
well eſteemed both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ect of time &amp; worth, even as the gifts and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of God
commended, yea commanded to be joyed in their good uſe, rather then neglected refuſed, As
ſerving alſo to many excellent uſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d purpoſes, even to increaſe in us divine and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>avenly joys and happines, of all which, I ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re alſo diſcourſe of ſomewhat more
particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rly.</p>
            <p>And firſt in reſpect of our ſelves, In that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e naturall and neceſſary to us.
Which appears <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their pleaſantneſſe, and variety of curious co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urs, harmonious
ſounds, pleaſant taſts, and fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rant ſmels which God hath particularly appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>riated to
every kinde of creature, affording ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her delight then neceſſity. But if wee conſider <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow
neceſſary they are alſo, As that wee cannot mayntain our ſelves, not live without them, we
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hall know, That they are to us of much worth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd therfore to be well eſteemed and freely
en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oyed in their good uſe.</p>
            <p>Neceſſity and pleaſure is an excellent Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge in Nature. And it is good reaſon that
thoſe actions which are neceſſary, ſhould alſo be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull, to which, as hath bin
ſaid, both Nature and Reaſon invites us, And therefore ſuch as goe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:9564:33"/> about to break this marriage, doe endevour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> diſunite that which
Reaſon and Nature ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> joyned together.</p>
            <p>Whence it may be inferr'd that ſuper flui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which is vain and vitious in all things being
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> chewed, we may not diſdain freely and cheerfu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to enjoy theſe earthly Pleaſures,
Recreatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Felicities, which God himſelf hath ordaine to be naturall, neceſſary and
pleaſant, and del<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctable to us.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in reſpect that they are the gifts an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bleſſings of God, ordained and created
for o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> good uſe &amp; enjoyance, &amp; which he lovingly of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fers up to our good uſe &amp;
acceptance, yea, com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mends &amp; commands the good uſe and enjoyanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> therof, as appears in the
former Section: There<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore to be well eſteemed, even as his gifts an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bleſſings, and in their
good uſe to be enjoyed freely and cheerfully.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, they are to be well eſteemed, as ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to many excellent uſes, to Gods glory.
And therin, to the good of our ſelves and others, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, as the mayntenance of our bodies and
mindes in due temper, and ſupernaturall, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as they may be an occaſion greatly to
en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe our heavenly joy and happineſſe. Of which I purpoſe to write particularly in the
laſt Se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:9564:33"/>So as although in compariſon of the heavenly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>licities, theſe of the earth
are vaine, ſhort, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>anſitory, and with the ſame not worthy to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mpared, yet without
ſuch compariſon, and in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſpect of our nature and neceſſities. And for as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch as they
are Gods gifts and bleſſings, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ended and commanded to be received and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oyed. And ſince
many good uſes may be made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hereof, to the increaſe of our happineſſe both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere and in
Heaven. Therefore they are to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>njoyed, And ſuch as either through ignorance,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eeviſhneſſe, or Superſtition do neglect and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe the enjoyance of theſe earthly
bleſſings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n their good uſe, are to be cenſured and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lamed.</p>
            <div type="abstract">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:9564:34"/>
               <head>The abſtract of the fifth SECTION.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THoſe ſouls which raiſed are above the skie</l>
                  <l>To heavenly glory, to Eternitie</l>
                  <l>In contemplations, do moſt certainly</l>
                  <l>Account earths joyes, but even as vanity.</l>
                  <l>In ſuch compariſon they truly deem</l>
                  <l>All earthly joys, not worthy their eſteem.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>While as their happy ſouls do thus aſpire</l>
                  <l>To heavenly joys, with flaming ſweet deſire</l>
                  <l>They do forget the earth, and being above</l>
                  <l>Themſelves inflam'd with heavenly joy and love,</l>
                  <l>They are ſo rapt in ſweet delights that even</l>
                  <l>They ſeem to taſte already joys of heaven.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So while their ſouls are rais'd above the Skie,</l>
                  <l>They ſeem to tread down very generouſly</l>
                  <l>All earthly joys beneath their feet as vain</l>
                  <l>Not worthy their eſteem, Their glorious aime.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And ſurely, no compariſon can be</l>
                  <l>Twixt earthly times, and heavens eternitie.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:9564:34"/>But though in ſuch compariſon, certainly</l>
                  <l>The greateſt earthly joys, are vanity.</l>
                  <l>Yet in themſelves, and alſo in reſpect</l>
                  <l>Of us, and our neceſſities, to neglect</l>
                  <l>And diſeſteem them, truly were a crime,</l>
                  <l>In ſuch respect, they are in worth and time</l>
                  <l>To be regarded: Yea to us they are given</l>
                  <l>By God himſelf, as tokens ſent from heaven.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Not onely for neceſſity, but delight,</l>
                  <l>Which doth appear becauſe unto our ſight</l>
                  <l>And all our ſences, they afford variety</l>
                  <l>Of delectations, even to ſatiety</l>
                  <l>Beyond neceſſity, and therfore they</l>
                  <l>Which ſuperſtitiouſly refuſe to enjoy</l>
                  <l>What God himſelf hath freely, kindly, given</l>
                  <l>Are worthy blame, though Saints, and heirs of heaven.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This is not all, he doth not onely give them</l>
                  <l>But lovingly commands us to receive them,</l>
                  <l>So as without abuſes, and annoyance</l>
                  <l>In their good uſe, and moderate enjoyance.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And alſo in ſuch joy they may invite</l>
                  <l>Attract, encourage, quicken, and excite</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:9564:35"/>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s unto all good actions, and to raiſe</l>
                  <l>Our ſouls to God himſelf, to heavenly joys</l>
                  <l>From whence theſe ſpring, and ſo to taſte, to finde</l>
                  <l>Pleaſures of heaven, on earth, within our minde:</l>
                  <l>So though earths joys be vain and tranſitory,</l>
                  <l>Yet may we therof, make us crowns of glory,</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="section">
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:9564:35"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The ſixt Section.</hi> Wee may enjoy earthly Happineſſe, notwithſtanding their
dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough it be moſt certain, there are many dangers and impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in earthly Riches,
Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and Pleaſures, yet theſe may be avoided, &amp; ſo c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nverted to our Felicity, in as
much as to eſchew and overcome them, or to endevour ſo to do, is acceptable to God, and by him
rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, And (ſince they are to us naturall, neceſſary commended and commanded by Reaſon
and Religion it ſelf as Gods creatures, gifts, and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings to be enjoyed in their good
uſes which are many, as hath bin ſhewed) their dangers and impediments hinder not, but wee may
enjoy them in their good uſe freely and cheerfully.</p>
            <p>But they which would mayntain the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:9564:36"/> truly tell us, Firſt, That earthly Riches, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Pleaſures are
dangerous, diſpoſing us to Covetouſneſſe, Ambition, Intemperance, and ſundry vices.</p>
            <p>But wee may truly anſwer, Although theſe earthly Felicities be dangerous, diſpoſing us
to ſuch vices. This is no ſufficient reaſon to divert us from the good uſe of them, It is
abſurd to ſay, A man may not uſe a Knife, becauſe ſome have cut their fingers therewith,
So to ſay wee ought not, to deſire Riches, Honor, &amp; Pleaſures in a moderate manner, And
ſo in their good uſe freely to enjoy them, becauſe they are an occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that ſome men
fall into Covetouſneſſe, Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Intemperance, and other vices, is an inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
Reaſon.</p>
            <p>The affections as one ſaith, Are the nerves and ſinews of the ſoule, They ſerve to
contract, to ſlacken, to lift up, to lay down, to ſtirre and ſettle the ſame, wherſoever
it will, even as the body is moved and removed by its ligaments, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are to be
preſerved and moderated, not taken away, and utterly deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>We are to imitate, in this, a well experienced Horſman, who for to tame and manage well his
horſe, will not take from him agilitie and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, but endevours eſpecially to bring him to
run, to turn, to riſe, to curvet, and to ſtand, how
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:9564:36"/> and when it pleaſeth him, and not according to the horſes will, even ſo
when wee perceive our affections inclining to ſtubborne diſobedience, we ought rather to
correct and reform the ſame with reaſon and judgement, then wholly to mortifie and extinguiſh
them,</p>
            <p>And although the Riches, Honour and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the earth be dangerous temptations to evill;
Yet for a man not be ill, where he hath no provocations therunto, is leſſe commendable, and
deſerving, then to be good in the midſt of dangers and temptations.</p>
            <p>Inſomuch that if we can make a good uſe even of theſe dangers and temptations by
overcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, or endevouring to overcome them (for God that accepts the will for the deed, will
lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vingly accept of our good wiſhes &amp; endevours, and his Power is made perfect in our
weakneſſe and infirmities, as (S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith) the ſame ſhall then convert to our
good and advancement, we ſhal be greatly rewarded in heaven, for ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt and
endevours, in ſuch good uſe therfore even of theſe dangers, we may take Saint <hi>James</hi>
exhortation, <hi>Count it all joy,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>when ye fall into divers
temptations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it is further objected to this purpoſe, by ſuch as would deny this truth. They truly
tell us, That we are exhorted in Gods ſacred Word to
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:9564:37"/> forſake, hate and overcome the World, and wee may alſo truly anſwer,
That ſurely it is not ment therin by forſaking, and hating the World, that wee ſhould goe
live in a Monaſtery, forſweare Marriage, Vow wilfull Poverty, refuſe lawfull meats, moderate
and expedient Recreations, and the like. But rather in the ſame ſenſe as wee are exhorted to
forſake &amp; hate father, mother, wife, children, &amp;c. That is for Chriſts ſake and the
Goſpels, rather then forſake him and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>By forſaking, hating and overcomming the World is meant the dangers, abuſes, and evils
therof, certainly not the good things therin in a ſuperſtitious manner. Theſe as hath bin
ſaid, may be enjoyed notwithſtanding their vanities and dangers in their good uſe freely and
cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully.</p>
            <p>To contemne, overcome and be above the World, is indeed a brave propoſition, and many there be
who glory to diſcourſe therof. Though perchance they ſcarce know what it is, much leſſe
practice it. The world is often dangerous and wanton in a corner, in ſolitarines, in idlenes and
in thoſe places and actions where ſome men make profeſſion of flying from it, and trampling
it underfoot, which is meant of Hypocrites who have ſo much degenerated from their beginning,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:9564:37"/> That there remayneth almoſt nothing but the habit, And that alſo ſerveth
to puffe them up; to make them proud and impudent, which is quite contrary to their
Inſtitutions.</p>
            <p>But to contemne the uſe, the ſervice, the commodity, and therin the enjoyance and
plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the World, what accuſation is it againſt Nature that invites us, againſt
Reaſon that wils us therunto, yea, againſt the Author that made them to theſe ends? What
ingratitude is it to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe that which God lovingly offers?</p>
            <p>To ſequeſter our ſelves from the company of the World, and from the enjoying of earthly
things, becauſe of their dangers, proceeds, as a Reverend Divine ſaith, from a weak, baſe,
and diſtruſtfull minde, as if we would ſo force good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe upon our ſelves, That
therfore onely wee would be good becauſe we cannot be ill, but for a man to know the higheſt of
worldly content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, To live in the throng of the World, and yet to be above it, to uſe it,
enjoy it &amp; contemne it, as he pleaſes, to compell it to his ſervice with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out infection,
well becomes the noble courage of a Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>No man indeed can ſerve two maſters,</hi> we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſerve God and Mammon, Let us then
make the World our ſlave, onely God our maſter.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:9564:38"/>It is true indeed, then, to be ſervants to the World, It is better to goe out
of it, but to uſe it as a Maſter compelling it to our ſervice, in all good ways without
abuſes, as it is more difficult then to ſequeſter our ſelves from it, ſo is it alſo
more victorious, and ſhall be an occaſion of greater triumphs and brighter Crowns in
Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
            <div type="abstract">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:9564:38"/>
               <head>The abſtract of the ſixt SECTION.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>ALthough 'tis certain, that terreſtriall treaſures</l>
                  <l>Honour and greatneſſe, alſo earthly pleaſures</l>
                  <l>Do greatly tempt us unto covetouſneſſe,</l>
                  <l>Ambition, all intemperate vitiouſneſſe.</l>
                  <l>Yet in good uſe therof, we freely may</l>
                  <l>The greateſt pleaſures therof, ſtill enjoy.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When our affections unto ill incline,</l>
                  <l>We ought with reaſon, and with grace divine</l>
                  <l>Such ill deſires to conquer and to quell,</l>
                  <l>It is more prayſe and glory, to do well.</l>
                  <l>In midſt of great tem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tations, then to be</l>
                  <l>Otherwiſe good, for meer neceſſity.</l>
                  <l>And as the danger's greater, we ſhall be</l>
                  <l>The more rewarded for ſuch victory.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Wheras to ſequeſter our ſelves for fear</l>
                  <l>Into a Monaſtery, or forbear</l>
                  <l>Things lawfull as expe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ient recreation</l>
                  <l>(Which may and ought with moderate delectation</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:9564:39"/>Be us'd) becauſe of dangers, doth proceed</l>
                  <l>Out of a weak diſtruſtfull minde indeed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But for a man to know the higheſt joy</l>
                  <l>The world affords, and yet without annoy</l>
                  <l>To live therin, and as a Maſter uſe</l>
                  <l>The ſame in all reſpects, without abuſe,</l>
                  <l>And can even as he liſt the world compell,</l>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto his ſervice, and even then do well</l>
                  <l>In midſt of great temptations, ſurely he</l>
                  <l>In heaven, with brighteſt glory crown'd ſhall be.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="section">
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:9564:39"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The ſeventh Section.</hi> Wee may enjoy earthly Felicities, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their
impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Vch men as object againſt the free and cheerfull enjoyance of earthly Felicities do truly
tell us, That the enjoyance and uſe of earthly happineſſe doth often hinder us in the
attainment, and alſo enjoyment of ſupernaturall and heavenly things.</p>
            <p>But we may alſo truly anſwer, &amp; are to know, That it is indeed onely the abuſes of
theſe Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and Felicities that hinder us therin, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in their good vſe, They
may ſerve as ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacles to ſeeth by the more cleerly into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:9564:40"/> and may further us in all good heavenly ways. They may ſtirre us up to
thankfulneſſe, and to all duties of pietie, encreaſe our love to God, and joy in him, They
may be notable en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements to do more worthily, and to go on more cheerfully in the ways of
God, and in ſuch good uſe they may be ſweet and pleaſant additions to our hope of heaven.
And by view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and enjoying theſe wee may look higher to their Fountain, contemplating the
excellency, ſweetneſſe and beauty of the Creator who is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely more excelling, and ſo
in ſome meaſure; eſpie and enjoy the Felicities of heaven alſo while we are on earth, but
of this more at large in the next Section. And therfore in their good uſe wee may enjoy them
freely and cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully.</p>
            <p>But ſuch as would mayntaine the contrary, do further object to this purpoſe more
particularly, The moſt materiall Objections I ſhall endevour to collect briefly, and ſo to
anſwere them, They truly tell us.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that Abſtinence and forbearance of pleaſures, doth beſt fit and prepare the minde
for the well performance of all divine Exerciſes and Contemplations.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that many ill men poſſeſſe and enjoy theſe e rthly Felicities, and many good
men
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:9564:40"/> want them, which ſhews, (ſay they) the ſame are hinderances in
goodneſſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that our Saviour ſaith, <hi>It is hard for a rich man to enter into heaven;</hi> And
Saint <hi>Paul, Not many mighty, not many noble are called,</hi> and that the mourners, the meek
and dejected ſpirits, are rather pronounced bleſſed in Gods Word, then voluptuous men.</p>
            <p>All which I ſhall endevour to anſwer briefly.</p>
            <p>Concerning the firſt, That faſting and forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of pleaſures, fits and prepares the
minde for divine Exerciſes. It is moſt true, and it is very requiſite and good that we
faſt, pray, repent, be abſtemious, and exerciſe our ſelves in all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian duties, ſo
far as we may conveniently with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuperſtition, as wee are exhorted therunto. And, God
forbid, that I ſhould be guilty of ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king againſt due and convenient faſting,
abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, and therin retiredneſſe from pleaſures of the World, to divine Contemplations,
which at due and convenient times, is certainly moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to God, And very beneficiall
both to body and minde, disburthening the ſame of many groſſe humours, vapours, and
ſpirits, and ſo taking away ſloth, dulnes, many diſtempers, &amp; making our minds, as
farre as is poſſible in this World, like Angels moſt free, quick, and ſprightly in the
performance of all divine Exerciſes, and ſo moſt
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:9564:41"/> apt and well prepared for the conceiving, Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and retayning of all
divine and heavenly illuminations and conſolations.</p>
            <p>But herein it is good to obſerve a due and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient order (as concerning faſting)
according to the preſcriptions and cuſtomes, of the Church and Saints in all Ages, to faſt
publikely, when Authority enjoyns us, ſometimes privatly accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our Saviours exhortation,
and the uſuall practice of religious Chriſtians, which is good to be done at, and in convenient
time, as ſomtimes forbearing a meale, ſomtimes a day, till night or the like, when, and ſo,
long as we may conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently and by our owne experience finde the ſame, doth make us beſt
prepared for all divine exerciſes and contemplations. And alſo upon good occaſions, It is not
good to make an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary exerciſe ordinary, which in ſome ſort takes away the
excellency therof. And becauſe it is an extraordinary exerciſe, extraordinary occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
beſt be fits the ſame.</p>
            <p>And ſo of other Chriſtian duties, a due and convenient order is to be obſerved in all of
them, according to that of the Wiſeman, There is a time for all things, a time to be dejected, a
time to mourn, a time to refraine from pleaſures, &amp;c. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>Yet ought wee not to be ſo ſuperſtitiouſly
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:9564:41"/> nice, as to refuſe Gods creatures, gifts, and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings which he freely
offers to our good uſe, and enjoyance, and ſo hinder and prejudice the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of our bodies
and mindes, through defect. But theſe earthly felicities alſo are to be uſed and enjoyed in
due order, and at convenient times, The Wiſe man alſo ſaith, <hi>There is a time to laugh, a
time to rejoyce, &amp;c.</hi> Eccleſ. 3.</p>
            <p>And commonly in the uſe and enjoyance of meat, drink, recreations, and all pleaſures, a
tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate cuſtome, as it is moſt beneficiall to the welfare of the body and minde. So alſo
is it moſt pleaſant, and ſuch men as ſo uſe and enjoy the ſame may be commonly
obſerved to be the moſt healthy, free, cheerfull, and happy men, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently apt, and
well prepared for the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of all good exerciſes of body, and minde, both humane and
heavenly.</p>
            <p>And the free and cheerfull enjoyance of earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly happineſſes alſo, may encourage and
ſtirre us up to all divine exerciſes, and may be an occaſion of many heavenly contemplations
and conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, as more plainly appeares in the laſt Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. And ſo further us in the
attainment, and alſo enjoyment of ſupernatuall and heavenly things, rather then hinder the
ſame, And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in ſuch good uſe, (notwithſtanding this
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:9564:42"/> objection) may at convenient times be enjoyed freely and cheerfully.</p>
            <p>It is true alſo as it is further objected, That many ill men enjoy earthly felicities and many
good men want them: And good reaſon for it becauſe of their dangers and impediments, as hath
been objected and anſwered. God like a wiſe Phyſician, a loving Father, often keeps his
ſervants from theſe things knowing (Perchance) the ſame will hurt them, for we are prone to
fall into abuſes and wickedneſſe: And we had much better never enjoy them, then abuſe them.
But theſe dangers, abuſes, and hinderances may be avoided, (Converted to our good, and
encreaſe our happines, as hath been ſhewed and anſwered before.</p>
            <p>Or perchance the reaſon why many good men want theſe may be to try, ſtirre up, quicken and
refine all heavenly graces in them, and ſo to encreaſe their glory and happineſſe in
Heaven, And the reaſon why ſome ill men enjoy them, may be for their greater mi ery and
puniſhment in the ill uſes of them, O perhaps leſt theſe earthly, ſhould be thought of
any value in reſpect of heavenly felicities, or divers other Reaſons beſt known to the
Almighty.</p>
            <p>Yet many good men alſo, as the moſt regular
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:9564:42"/> Philoſophers and greateſt profeſſors of verrue, <hi>Zeno, Cato,
Scipio, Epaminondas, Plato, Socrates</hi> himſelf and divers others have uſed, enjoyed, and
written in commendation of love, and other ſports, delights and pleaſures. Likewiſe
<hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Job, Solomon,</hi> and innumerable others have poſſeſſed and enjoyed theſe
earthly Felicities. And ſomtimes Chriſt himſelf (as at the Marriage in <hi>Cana</hi>) would
uſe and approve of the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of earthly creatures leſt they ſhould be thought evill.</p>
            <p>Being indeed of themſelves good, but of an indifferent nature to us, good, or evill, as they
are well uſed or abuſed. But being well uſed with mediocrity and to good ends. They are
with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out queſtion, rather to be uſed and enjoyed then deſpiſed or neglected, <hi>Vnto the
pure all things are pure,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Paul.</hi> And again, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.14. <hi>I
know and am perſwaded by the Lord Jeſus</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>That there is nothing unclean of
it ſelfe, But to him that eſteemeth any thing unclean, to him it is unclean;</hi> and in the
ſame Chapter hee intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, <hi>Such to be the weaker Chriſtians who are nice and
ſcrupulous in theſe things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet however wee ought not to deſpiſe ſuch men who refuſe the moderate uſe of earthly
bleſſings: Saint <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l</hi> adviſeth ſo, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.2, 10, 13.
<hi>Foraſmuch</hi> (as he ſaith) <hi>aſwell ſuch as eate,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:9564:43"/> or drink, or ſuch as refuſe, both do it to pleaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God, and to give God
thanks.</hi> Wherfore it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, Although ſuch refuſall be ſuperſtition, and folly, in
ſuch men, yet ſith they do it to pleaſe God, we ought not to deſpiſe, or judge them, But
rather reſpect and wel eſteem them, for their good intents and purpoſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let no man judge you in reſpect of meate or drinke, or of an holy day, or of the new
Moone, or Sabbath days,</hi> Col. 2.16.</p>
            <p>True it is we reade of many ancient Fathers, and holy men who have been very ſtrict and
ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervant in the refuſall of riches, of honour, of dainty meats, fleſh, wine, marriage, and
all plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and lived in Deſerts, Cels, and Monaſteries very abſtemiouſly, eating
very ſeldome, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring onely with bread, water, herbs, or other courſe meat, And of Saint
<hi>John Baptiſt</hi> who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a very auſtere life, <hi>Whoſe garments were one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of
Camels haire, and girdle of skins, his meat Locuſts and wild honey,</hi> Of whom our Saviour
ſaith, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11. <hi>That he came neither eating nor drinking,</hi> and blamed them who
therfore ſaid, <hi>he had a Devill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherfore wee are to reverence and well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of the ſevere ſanctitie of thoſe ancient
Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and holy men (reſpecting their good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, being intended and done to the glory of
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:9564:43"/> God, and in and through Chriſt Ieſus gloriouſly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ewarded) yet wee may as
much admire thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thers, as devou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and of like ſanctity, who imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ate our Saviour, He ſaith
of him (after hee had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>old of Saint <hi>John Baptiſts</hi> ſeverity as before, <hi>Matth.</hi>
11.) <hi>That the Sonne of man came eating and drinking,</hi> But being with temperance and
moderation, Hee blamed thoſe which therfore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aid, <hi>Behold, a man gluttonous, and a
Wine-bib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ber, a friend of Publicans and ſinners,</hi> concluding, <hi>But wiſdome is
juſtified of her children,</hi> implying his innocency, And that there ought to be a wiſe
moderation in all things.</p>
            <p>Now ſuch as imitate our Saviour, and thoſe ancient Chriſtians in the Primitive times,
<hi>Who did eate their meate together with gladneſſe and ſingleneſſe of heart,</hi> And
thoſe who reſorted to thoſe ancient Feaſts and Banquets of Charity, of whom I have written
before, and others ſince in all ages vertuous and religious Chriſtians of all degrees, who have
not diſdained to enjoy theſe gifts and bleſſings of God in their good uſe, are much
better to be reputed then ſuch as refuſe ſo much good, which God lovingly and freely offers
to our acceptance, good uſe, &amp; enjoyance.</p>
            <p>Such therfore who can live in the World, and yet be ſo ſpirituall and heavenly minded,
<hi>That they can uſe it as if they uſed it not,</hi> how, &amp; when
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:9564:44"/> they pleaſe for their owne advantage, Who ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be temperate like our Saviour
amongſt <hi>Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans and ſinners,</hi> or as <hi>Lot,</hi> be a good man in
<hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such as know theſe earthly Felicities in their higheſt excellency and pleaſures, And yet
can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void their evils, dangers and impediments, and in all good ways uſe them or contemne them
as they will themſelves, Such men indeed are moſt worthy of prayſe, and to be eſteemed
moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving.</p>
            <p>And this to do, is a greater glory, and ſhews much more and ſtronger ſanctity and grace
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, then utterly to abandon the World by retyring to a Monaſtery, or to neglect Gods gifts
and bleſſings, and conſequently ſhall be more gloriouſly rewarded in Heaven.</p>
            <p>Wheras it is alſo further objected, That our Saviour ſaith, <hi>It is hard for a rich man to
enter into heaven.</hi> And Saint <hi>Paul, Not many noble, not many mightie are called,
&amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. The Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is becauſe riches and greatneſſe are great
dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and impediments, And therfore the former anſwers may ſerve to this objection
alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Not many mighty, not many noble are called af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fleſh,</hi> ſaith the Text. If a
mighty and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man can be ſpirituall and heavenly, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the temptations of the
fleſh, and the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:9564:44"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>llurements of Riches and Greatneſſe, which na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urally draw our deſires
downwards, He is a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le and worthy man indeed. Thrice bleſſed are thoſe rich, mighty, and
noble men who can over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome ſuch great temptations to evill, as great honour and riches allure
unto, It is a greater glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to mount up to heaven, through impediments, through great temptations
and difficulties then otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>Wheras it is alſo objected, That the Mourners the meek, and dejected ſpirits are rather
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced bleſſed in Gods Word then voluptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men, It is true indeed our Saviour ſaith,
<hi>Bleſſed are they that mourne, for they ſhall be comforted, Bleſſed are the meeke in
ſpirit, for theirs is the Kingdome of God,</hi> But theſe are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, words of
bleſſedneſſe, of comfort, and of exultation, To ſuch as are truly penitent and meek in
ſpirit, exciting them to faith, to hope, to joy and cheerfulneſſe.</p>
            <p>It is an error to think and mayntain that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion dejects us, wee ſee the ſame is
ſufficient to cheer, quicken and comfort, the mourners, the lowly and dejected ſpirits, and to
rayſe their joys as high as a Kingdome, as Heaven. For moſt ſweetly and happily doth it teach
us, That ſuch men are bleſſed, They ſhall be comforted, to them belongeth the Kingdome of
God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:9564:45"/>Religion indeed tels us, wee ought to mourn and be dejected, for our ſins and
frailties, rathe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> then always to enjoy the Pleaſures &amp; Felicitie of the World, But this
alſo is to be done in du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> order, and at convenient times, as hath bin ſaid <hi>There is a time
to mourne, and a time to rejoyce Eccles.</hi> 3. And indeed even true repentance and humiliation,
in its deepeſt ſorrows ought incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently to worke in us a ſound and joyfull aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
of reconciliation to God, in conſideration of his infinite mercy in IESVS CHRIST to his penitent
believing creatures; and ſo to open unto us the ſweet Fountaines of joy and cheefulneſſe
rather then dejectus, cauſing in us a happy and bleſſed tranquillity, and exalting our joys
even to the Heavens.</p>
            <p>And although it be moſt true, that Religion ought to make us deny our ſelves, And to ſee
our ſelves, like the <hi>Laodiceans;</hi> poore, miſerable, blinde, wretched, and naked, yet of
Chriſt Ieſus, (who counſels us therunto, <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.18.) Wee may buy fine gold, white
rayment, eye-ſalve, in him therfore we may be, and ought to think our ſelves, rich,
bleſſed, happy, the beloved of God himſelf, and heirs of Heaven.</p>
            <p>This heavenly joy and exultation of Spirit within us, may alſo adde to the free and cheerfull
enjoyance of earthly Felicities, in as much as we
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:9564:45"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay enjoy the ſame, with a more happy, free, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eerfull minde, for why, a
gracious, high ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, joyfull, heavenly minde enjoys all things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore ſweetly, pleaſantly,
nobly and excellently, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en a low dejected minde, which onely creeps <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the earth, and can raiſe
it ſelf no higher.</p>
            <p>Doth not then Religion, moſt ſweetly and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inely teach us to be contented, pleaſed, and
hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, in all eſtates, and conditions, ſo that whether <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee be afflicted, mourn, dejected,
looſe, want, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave ſufficiency, or abundance wee may thinke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur ſelves happy in all things.
<hi>Having firſt ſought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he kingdome of God, and the righteouſneſſe therof,</hi> wee may
now freely enjoy earthly happineſſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lſo, as little additions to that great hope, which we
may and ought to have of thoſe infinite and eternall felicities of Heaven.</p>
            <p>It is an errour therfore to mayntaine as ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave done, that men (though Gods ſervants)
(ſhould not enjoy earth and heaven alſo. What a groſſe abſurdity is it to think that the
felicities of the earth (which many wicked men enjoy) ſhould not be poſſeſt and enjoyed by
Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants in their good uſe freely and cheerfully, ſince he lovingly offers the ſame,
and for whoſe good uſe and enjoyance they were created, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.4.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:9564:46"/>
               <hi>Being reconciled to God in Chriſt, what good what happineſſe is in
Earth or Heaven, That we may not enjoy, for now all things are ours, and we are Chriſts, and
Chriſt is GODS.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="abstract">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:9564:46"/>
               <head>The abſtract of the fourth SECTION.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>ALthough that many hinderances be</l>
                  <l>In earthly riches, honours, pleaſures; We</l>
                  <l>In their good uſe without abuſes may</l>
                  <l>Them notwithſtanding, cheerfully enjoy.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>'Tis not their uſe, but onely their abuſes</l>
                  <l>That hinder us in goodneſſe, their good uſes</l>
                  <l>May further us in all good happy ways,</l>
                  <l>And be occaſions, to direct our joyes</l>
                  <l>To God himſelf, to heaven, from whence they ſpring</l>
                  <l>And ſo whilſt we are ſweetly ſolacing</l>
                  <l>Our ſelves in thoughts of God, of Heaven, we may</l>
                  <l>In ſome degree, pleaſures of heaven, enjoy.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>'Tis true indeed that moderate abſtinence</l>
                  <l>So as the ſame be with convenience</l>
                  <l>Disburthens, Our groſſe mindes and makes them lightfull,</l>
                  <l>Perspicuous, free, moſt quick, and very ſprightfull,</l>
                  <l>Apt to receive all heavenly inſpirations</l>
                  <l>And to retain divine illuminations.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:9564:47"/>
                  <l>But too much abſtinence, beyond due meaſure</l>
                  <l>And over-nice reſtraint of lawfull pleaſure</l>
                  <l>Doth much perplex the minde, and ſo annoyes</l>
                  <l>The ſame in all good Actions, heavenly joys.</l>
                  <l>And herein order, time, occaſion, is,</l>
                  <l>To be obſerved leſt, we do amiſſe.</l>
                  <l>But uſually, a temperate cuſtomes beſt</l>
                  <l>And ſuch as uſe the ſame are ſurely bleſt,</l>
                  <l>No men do live more free, and healthfully</l>
                  <l>More joyfull, cheerfull, and more happily</l>
                  <l>More apt in minde, to all good actions, than</l>
                  <l>He that is uſually a temperate man:</l>
                  <l>In ſuch a man all earthly pleaſures may</l>
                  <l>Beſt ſerve to excite good actions, heavenly joy.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Such men indeed are worthy of moſt praiſe</l>
                  <l>Who can their minds to ſuch a temper raiſe</l>
                  <l>To know and ſee the higheſt ſweeteſt joy</l>
                  <l>The World affords, and yet without annoy</l>
                  <l>To live therin, and as a Maſter uſe</l>
                  <l>The ſame (in all reſpects without abuſe)</l>
                  <l>As if he us'd it not, Even how and when</l>
                  <l>He will himſelf enjoying now and then</l>
                  <l>Its choiſeſt pleaſures, when he pleaſe again</l>
                  <l>Contemning them, even with a great diſdain</l>
                  <l>For's own advantage, when his ſoule aſpires</l>
                  <l>To Heaven, comparing them with ſuch deſires</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:9564:47"/>
                  <l>He then contemplates, ſurely ſuch a man</l>
                  <l>Who thin doth uſe all earthly joys, and can,</l>
                  <l>Be good, as <hi>Lot</hi> in <hi>Sodome,</hi> or as Chriſt,</l>
                  <l>Be temperate, even at the Sinners Feaſt,</l>
                  <l>And ſurely ſuch heroick noble hearts</l>
                  <l>As can be good amongst a ſhowre of darts,</l>
                  <l>As alſo ſuch as not withſtanding Quires</l>
                  <l>Of Syrens tempting unto ill deſires</l>
                  <l>Can yet be chaſt, and temperate, ſhall be</l>
                  <l>Rewarded greatly, for ſuch victory</l>
                  <l>In Heaven with ineſtimable treaſures</l>
                  <l>With Crowns of glory, with eternall pleaſures,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Moſt certainly indeed, thrice bleſſed then</l>
                  <l>Are ſuch great mighty, rich and noble men,</l>
                  <l>Who notwithſtanding many ſtrong temptation.</l>
                  <l>Alluring and inchanting provocations.</l>
                  <l>Can yet (contemning evils) mount the Skies</l>
                  <l>To heaven through al theſe charming difficultie.</l>
                  <l>O how ſuch men, in heaven eternally</l>
                  <l>Shall ſweetly triumph for ſuch victory.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It is an error to maintain, and ſay</l>
                  <l>Religion doth deject us, truly nay.</l>
                  <l>Religion ſure doth comfort, quicken, cheare,</l>
                  <l>It doth encourage, elevate up reare.</l>
                  <l>Mourning dejected Spirits very high,</l>
                  <l>Even to a kingdome far above the skie,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="76" facs="tcp:9564:48"/>To Heaven it ſelf, and ſweetly doth poſſeſſe</l>
                  <l>Them, with true peace, true joy, true happineſſe,</l>
                  <l>It alſo makes earth's happineſſe farre ſweeter</l>
                  <l>So as we may enjoy the ſame, much better:</l>
                  <l>For when ſuch raiſed heavenly joys we finde,</l>
                  <l>We may enjoy the earth, with heavenly minde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So having ſought Gods Kingdome, now we may</l>
                  <l>The Pleaſures of the earth freely enjoy.</l>
                  <l>In ſuch ſort, as we may eſteem them even,</l>
                  <l>Little additions to our hope of Heaven.</l>
                  <l>Since we are Chriſts, and Ghriſt is Gods, we may</l>
                  <l>The ſweeteſt joyes, on earth, in Heaven enjoy.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="section">
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:9564:48"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The eighth Section.</hi> Wee may enjoy earthly happineſſe with a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly mind,
inſomuch as by the good uſe and enjoyance therof, we may learn and enjoy in ſome meaſure,
the felicities of heaven, on earth.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have in the former Sections, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted ſomewhat largely upon the free and cheerfull
enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of earthly happineſſe in their good uſe, anſwering the objections to the
contrary, The rather, becauſe certainly, If men were well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of this truth, That
externall happineſſe is not contrary, but rather in the good uſe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, may be a
furtherance, both to internall and eternall happineſſe, They would with more ſwift deſires,
run the ways that lead them, both to the felicities of earth and heaven. And alſo becauſe the
too rigid and ſtoicall, ſeverity of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:9564:49"/> men, both in their carriage and writings, is a great occaſion, That
multitudes of people in the World, eſpecially ſuch as are young, and of a pleaſant nature,
will not follow the divine Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of verue and Religion, thinking the ſame too ſevere,
Monkiſh and ſolitary.</p>
            <p>Wheras indeed the ways of religion and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, are moſt lovely, pleaſant, and beneficiall,
Her ways are ways of Pleaſantneſſe, and her paths are peace, <hi>Proverb.</hi> 3.17. The
ſame is ſufficient to guerdon the followers therof, even in this life, with perfect pleaſure,
and a multitude of bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits. It is no way deficient, but in all reſpects a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miable and excellent.
Adding to the pleaſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and delights of earthly pleaſures, felicities, and
recreations, and making theſe alſo ſerve to encreaſe heavenly joys and conſolations. And
when our mindes are raiſed to the knowledge of heavenly pleaſures, wee may then alſo enjoy
the felicities of the earth, with a heavenly mind.</p>
            <p>Let us therfore endevour by and through theſe lower delights and happineſſes of the earth,
Theſe little glimmering rays, proceeding from that Sun of Glory God himſelf, to eſpie ſome
light of his havenly Glory and Happineſſe, and ſo in ſome meaſure to ſpell, learn, and
enjoy the felicities of heaven, on earth.</p>
            <p>Wee are not to diſdain, to make uſe of theſe
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:9564:49"/> earthly, in the acquiſt of heavenly things, nor to make earthly
compariſons, and ſimilitudes here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, For although there be no compariſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them,
either in Time or Excellency. Yet (as children have need at firſt to be allured to the
acquiſition of great and excellent matters, by ſuch toyes and trifles as they apprehend ſo)
in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of our weake apprehenſion, ſuch compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and ſimilitudes often are, and
may be uſed in a convenient manner.</p>
            <p>So as we may make a very good uſe of earthly felicities in this reſpect (as of a
proſpective Glaſſe) for by and through theſe earthly, our weak ſight may ſee more
plainly into heavenly happineſſes, and conſequently be excited to ſeek and enjoy the
ſame.</p>
            <p>Let us then, by reaſons light, through theſe terreſtriall endevour to learn, eſpie, and
contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate higher, more excellent, heavenly happines. Reaſon is of ſuch force, as that it can
paſſe from things known, to things unknown, It can ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract from, viſible things, things
inviſible, from corporall, incorporall, generals, from particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars: and high, myſticall, and
heavenly things, from low apparant terreſtriall things. So as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may in ſome meaſure
contemplate, God himſelf and his heavenly Glory.</p>
            <p>It is a common doctrine, the World is made
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:9564:50"/> for man, and man for God, and that there is no happineſſe in the World
from which wee may not draw ſome inſtruction, to know God, our ſelves and our dutie. If
therfore, (firſt in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall) we conſider all the Felicities in the World, in their greateſt
worth, beauty, ſweetneſſe and pleaſantneſſe, reaſon will tell us, That if there be
ſo much excellency in the creatures, the Creator is in all reſpects much more excellent, and
that if we may enjoy ſuch, and ſo many pleaſures and felicities in creatures. Much more, and
better may, and ſhall we enjoy in God himſelf, &amp; taſte and ſee, how good the Lord is,
ſaith King <hi>David.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Felicities of the Earth in their greateſt worth and excellency, Are but as drops
procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from the ocean of his infinite ſweetneſſe, If we may enjoy ſo much pleaſure,
ſo much hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines in theſe little drops &amp; foretaſts, how much more may &amp; ſhal we,
in thoſe rivers of pleaſures, in that ſea of happineſſe, which is in God in the heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.
Reaſon alſo tels us, If there be ſo much, ſo many, &amp; ſuch excellent treaſures,
glory, delights, and felicities, on earth, the place of our mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, of our pilgrimage,
poſſeſſed alſo by Gods e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, There is abundantly more happineſſe in Heaven, the
place of our Eternity, our Kingdom, and poſſeſſed onely by God himſelfe and his
Friends.</p>
            <p>And beſides the inſtruction which man draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:9564:50"/> in generall from earthly Felicities, hee may, likewiſe in particulars, even
by reaſon, ſpie and learn ſome knowledge of God himſelf, and his heavenly glory and
happineſſe.</p>
            <p>As for example, The azur'd Heaven ſo richly deckt and counterpointed with Stars and row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
Torches, never ceaſing over our heads, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying the ſame by contemplation, he mounteth higher,
and is carried with admiration, feare, love, and reverence of the Authour, and ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord
of all; So that we can, even by our corporall eys from the Earth, look to the Moon, the Sun, the
ſtarry Heaven, and therein ſweetly pleaſe our ſelves in the view and contemplation of their
glorious aſpect, Their bright, lovely, twinkling, ſilver, heavenly rays, from thence by the eye
of reaſon, wee can ſee further, to the Chriſtalline Heaven; yea, to the Emperiall above the
Spheres, and there contemplate farre more excellent glory, delights, and happineſſe.</p>
            <p>So as even by reaſon, in, and through theſe earthly Felicities our dim eyes (as through
ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacles) may eſpy ſome light of God himſelfe, and of his infinite beauty,
ple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſantneſſe, ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and excellency.</p>
            <p>But if wee adde the eie of Faith alſo to our Reaſon, wee may view farther and ſee more
plainly. This Author of all happineſſe God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:9564:51"/> and his Celeſtiall glory. And taſte of the ocean of his infinite
ſweetneſſe and heavenly pleaſures.</p>
            <p>And, as Reaſon, ſo faith alſo, in the view and contemplation of heaven may make a very
good uſe of earthly compariſons, ſimilitudes, delights, and happineſſe, Wee often finde
in the ſacred Scriptures, that earthly compariſons are uſed to expreſſe heavenly
excellencies to our apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, So as by the Riches, Honour, Kingdomes, Crowns, Glory,
Delights, and Pleaſures of the Earth, wee may looke infinitely higher, by the light of Reaſon
and of Faith, and therby con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template thoſe infinitely more excellent, Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, Crowns,
Kingdomes, Glory and Delights of Heaven.</p>
            <p>Faith goes before time, and makes things fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, preſent, in ſuch ſort as therby we may,
even in this life in ſome degree poſſeſſe the happineſſe of Heaven, in ſo much as
by faithfull and heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contemplation, we may even ſet our ſouls in Heaven before-hand,
taſting already of future happineſſe, entertayning our ſelves, with God himſelf and with
Angels. And ſo enjoying in our thoughts and contemplations, a Paradiſe of heavenly Pleaſures
and Felicities on earth.</p>
            <p>Let us therfore often in contemplation, by the light of Reaſon and of Faith (which are the
beſt
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:9564:51"/> Opticks) view and contemplate thoſe glorious Crowns, Treaſures, Delights
&amp; Felicities, which wee expect hereafter to poſſeſſe in the Heavens, and as in a
mirrour behold his glory, who is the fountain &amp; Perfection of al pleaſure &amp; happines.</p>
            <p>It is the poore, deſpiſed, and miſerable mans, onely hope and joy on earth, To be rich,
hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and happy in Heaven. The rich, honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and proſperous man alſo, with reaſon
ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines, That if Terreſtriall Proſperity afford him ſome Felicities and Pleaſures, Hee
ſhall be much more happy, when he ſhall poſſeſſe thoſe eternall Riches, Honours and
Pleaſures of Heaven.</p>
            <p>Let our ſouls then often ſoare aloft upon the wings of Reaſon and of Faith, unto the
Empi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rean Heaven, where our deſires ſhall be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed with all manner of Felicities;
Would we have Thrones? This Imperiall Heaven ſhall be our Footſtool, Would wee have Crownes?
Glory and Immortality ſhall environ our heads? Do we deſire Treaſures? Ineſtimable riches
are in this houſe of our God, Would we have Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures? Rivers of pleaſures are at his right
hand for evermore.</p>
            <p>Let us then untie our ſelves from the covetous, ambitious, intemperate, and vitious deſire
of theſe earthly Felicities, and with a Pitch full of deſire, and love, elevate our Thoughts to
thoſe
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:9564:52"/> moſt glorious, Riches, Kingdomes, and Pleaſures of Heaven.</p>
            <p>The riches of the World, ſo much as wee do poſſeſſe, In the good uſe therof let us
ſtill enjoy freely, and cheerfully, onely let us convert our covetous, baſe, ſordid, and
vitious deſire therof, To the love, deſire, and enjoyance of a contented minde, and of the
riches of divine grace, Thoſe eternall Treaſures of Heaven; yea even to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe God
himſelfe, In ſuch deſires let us greatly rejoyce.</p>
            <p>So alſo Honour, and good repute, may we ſtill enjoy, And inſtead of that ravenous, and
unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiable thirſt, of ayry and vain honour, compoſed of Pride, Vain-glory, Hypocriſie, and
ſundry vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Let every one of us aſpire (by the aſſiſtance of the Divine Power) to be
Lord of himſelf, The Worlds Maſter, To triumph over all infernall Powers, To be a Sonne of God,
an heire to the Kingdome of Heaven. And in ſuch deſires and aſpirations, Let us take
marvellous joy and Pleaſure.</p>
            <p>All lawfull and good pleaſures alſo in ſuch good uſe, let us freely enjoy, onely let us
convert our vain, vitious, unlawfull intemperate deſire ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, To deſire and wiſh for,
thoſe moſt ſweet pleaſures, which proceed from a happy tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the ſoule and joy
in God, and to taſte in
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:9564:52"/> ſome meaſure before hand of that divine Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, that celeſtiall Nectar,
thoſe fountaines of Pleaſures which wee hope and expect to enjoy with God himſelf for ever in
the Heavens.</p>
            <p>Let us then freely and cheerfully, walke into this terreſtriall Paradiſe, the vaſt Palace
of the World, and enjoy the felicities thereof, for to this end they were created, that we ſhould
uſe them well, and ſo enjoy them.</p>
            <p>Even the meaneſt delights therof, were ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for this purpoſe, and may be of excellent
uſe, As for example,</p>
            <p>The chirping of Birds, who learn to ſing of Nature, to charme our eares, through the ſweet
harmony of their warbling, when theſe pleaſe our eares, then may we think of the ſweet
Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, of Saints and Angels which ſhall raviſh our ſpirits.</p>
            <p>And the Fountaines, though inſenſible, yet ſtrive with the ſweet murmurs of their prety
purlings, to afford us delectation. When this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights our thoughts, Then may we contemplate
thoſe heavenly Fountains of Life, which ſhall fill us with extreme delectation for ever.</p>
            <p>In this Terreſtriall Palace, the Spring, the Summer, and Autumne, are inceſſantly buſied
in producing our happineſſe, for a ſeaſon, but let us think in the Celeſtiall Paradiſe,
an Eternitie
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:9564:53"/> ſhall accompliſh us with more felicity then we can imagine.</p>
            <p>Here we ſee the Sun, Moon, Stars, The Skies, Fire, Torches, Pearles, Gold, and divers other
glorious ſights and beauties, Let us then think of that Glory, of which if wee could (with Saint
<hi>Peter</hi>) eſpie but one ray, wee ſhould like him be ſo dazeled at the glittering
thereof, as wee ſhould for ever deſire to dwell there, and to build Tabernacles.</p>
            <p>When we ſee and taſte of ſweet and pleaſant Cates, Banquetting, Feſtivall and dainty
meats, of all ſorts, of ſparkling and delicious wines, and other pleaſing liquors, Let us
then think of that Celeſtiall Manna, the food of Heaven, of that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nectar, the
ſweetneſſe of eternall joy and happineſſe, That everlaſting Lovefeaſt, to which the
Angels ſhall invite us, and where wee ſhall enjoy infinite pleaſures and happineſſe for
ever.</p>
            <p>This divine Manna, this heavenly Nectar, if we could but taſte therof, but truly think therof
indeed, it were ſufficient to charme our ſpirits, and ſweetly to bring them into a moſt
pleaſing extaſie. In ſo much, that in ſuch heavenly thoughts and contemplations, wee may
already in ſome meaſure feaſt on the joyes of Eternity, taſte of the delights of Heaven, on
Earth.</p>
            <p>And ſo I might inſtance, in a thouſand other occaſionall Meditations.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:9564:53"/>Thus if wee can uſe theſe Terreſtriall happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, well we may
freely and cheerfully enjoy the ſame, Even with a divine, a heavenly minde, and they may further
us in the attainment, and alſo enjoyment of heavenly delights and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe.</p>
            <p>And when wee have made ſuch a good uſe of them, as Children do of their <hi>A, B, C,</hi>
and Battle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore, or of toyes and trifles, ſuch as they appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, By theſe Learning and
comming to the knowledge of farre more excellent matters, and afterwards ſeeing themſelves
beyond, and above them, do even contemne theſe, in compariſon of the more excellent things,
which they have then learned, yet ſtill ſcorn not to uſe theſe Letters, and Rudiments of
Learning, But ſo, as that they can be above them, and uſe them as they liſt, for their own
advantage.</p>
            <p>So let us, having by theſe earthly felicities ſpelled and learned eternall and heavenly
Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies, endevour to be above and even to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne theſe earthly, in compariſon of the
hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly felicities which are infinitely more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, yet ſo, as that without ſuch
compariſon and in reſpect of our nature and neceſſities of their Author, And their good
uſe, wee ſtill eſteeme them wel accordingly; ſtil uſe them for our own advantage, And
ſo in all reſpects, to increaſe our
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:9564:54"/> joy and happineſſe, ſtill endevouring by theſe (as by Letters) to read
and learne further into thoſe infinitely more excellent, treaſures, Glory, and delights of
Heaven.</p>
            <p>And certain it is; that thoſe ſouls which are raiſed to a ſupernaturall and divine
temper, to a high degree of knowledge and contemplation in the heavenly felicities, are the moſt
happy men, even in this World, in as much as they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the happineſſes of the earth, with a
gracious, creared, cheerfull, joyfull, and heavenly minde, and alſo do in ſome meaſure
already taſte of and enjoy, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hoſe felicities which they pretend to receive hereafter, and to
enjoy eternally while their ſouls are here, ſolacing themſelves in the contemplations of
Heaven.</p>
            <p>In ſo much that even on earth in ſuch divine Contemplations, we may ſet our ſpirits in
Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, enjoying alſo a Paradiſe of heavenly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and happineſſe, Taſting in
ſome degree the delights of Heaven beforehand, ſo as it ſeems we may enjoy two Heavens, The
firſt Heaven on Earth, the other Heaven, in Heaven, Aſcending at the end of the Careere of this
life, from one Heaven to another, from this Terreſtriall, to the Celeſtiall Paradiſe.</p>
            <div type="abstract">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:9564:54"/>
               <head>The abſtract of the eighth SECTION:</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>SEe then, Religious lovely pleaſantneſſe,</l>
                  <l>It crowns us every way with happineſſe.</l>
                  <l>It addes unto earths joyes and recreations,</l>
                  <l>And makes theſe adde to heavenly conſolations.</l>
                  <l>And when ſuch heavenly joys, in us we finde</l>
                  <l>We may enjoy the Earth with heavenly minde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When we in earthly bleſſings take delight</l>
                  <l>We may look higher, thence direct our ſight</l>
                  <l>Above the Sphears, to God himſelf, to Heaven</l>
                  <l>From whence theſe come, and there contemplate even</l>
                  <l>The eternall glory which we ſhall poſſeſſe,</l>
                  <l>Even God himſelf, and heavenly happineſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For by the eye of reaſon our dimme ſight,</l>
                  <l>May through theſe earthly pleaſures ſpie ſome light</l>
                  <l>Of heavenly joys, and ſo may be excited</l>
                  <l>To taſte therof, To which we are invited</l>
                  <l>O taſte and ſee how good the Lord is, ſaith</l>
                  <l>King <hi>David,</hi> Then, by Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſon, and by Faith</l>
                  <l>Let us look up to Heaven; If we conſider</l>
                  <l>The ſweeteſt Pleaſures, of the World together,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:9564:55"/>
                  <l>Reaſon will tell us, If in creatures bee</l>
                  <l>Such excellency, much more may we ſee,</l>
                  <l>Taſte and enjoy, In the Creators worth.</l>
                  <l>From whence, as little drops, theſe do ſpring forth</l>
                  <l>If in theſe drops, ſome pleaſures we do take</l>
                  <l>How more ſhall we, in that mightie Lake</l>
                  <l>That Sea of ſweetneſſe, which we ſhall poſſeſſe</l>
                  <l>In God himſelf, and heavenly happineſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If on the Earth, ſo many Pleaſures be,</l>
                  <l>Which is the place of our mortalitie,</l>
                  <l>Much more delights in Heaven ſhall we ſee</l>
                  <l>Which is the place of our Eternitie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When we the azur'd Heaven, richly deckt</l>
                  <l>With glorious rowling Torches, whoſe aſpect</l>
                  <l>Doth often mount our mindes in Contemplation,</l>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p to their Author, and with Admiration</l>
                  <l>With reverence, with feare, with joy, and love,</l>
                  <l>To think of him their Lord, who dwels above</l>
                  <l>All theſe, we then, with reaſon muſt confeſſe</l>
                  <l>He is all wiſdom, power and happineſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We can with our Corporeall, look even</l>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the Sphears, viewing thoſe lights of heaven,</l>
                  <l>The Sun, the Moon, and twinkling ſtars, ſo bright,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe lovely, glorious, ſilver, heavenly light</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="91" facs="tcp:9564:55"/>Gives pleaſing delectation; from thence higher</l>
                  <l>Our ſprightly ſouls, by reaſons light aſpire</l>
                  <l>To the Imperiall Heaven, where we may</l>
                  <l>Contemplate marvailous glory, heavenly joy.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So as through earthly pleaſures, our dull ſight</l>
                  <l>May (as through Spectacles) by reaſons light</l>
                  <l>Look up to Heaven, to God himſelf and ſpie</l>
                  <l>Some glimpſes of his glorious Majeſtie</l>
                  <l>And ſo may taſte already, in ſome meaſure</l>
                  <l>The Ocean of his ſweet and heavenly pleaſure.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But if we adde faiths light, to reaſons eye</l>
                  <l>We then may far more plainly, cleerly, ſpie</l>
                  <l>The glory of God; his bright celeſtiall treaſures</l>
                  <l>And taſt the ſweetneſſe of his heavenly pleaſures.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Faith's, of ſuch power, ſuch force, as that it can</l>
                  <l>Make future things, ſeem preſent to a man</l>
                  <l>It prevents time, ſo as therby we may</l>
                  <l>Pleaſures of Heaven, in ſome degree enjoy</l>
                  <l>Beforehand, ſetting our bleſt ſouls in Heaven</l>
                  <l>In faithfull contemplations, therin, even</l>
                  <l>Our ſelves with God, and Angels entertayning</l>
                  <l>And in ſuch glorius heavenly thoughts, remayning</l>
                  <l>Moſt ſweetly pleas'd and joyfull. Thus we may</l>
                  <l>On earth, a heavenly Paradiſe enjoy.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:9564:56"/>
                  <l>Let's often then by faith, and reaſons light:</l>
                  <l>From earth unto the Heavens direct or ſight</l>
                  <l>And there contemplate on thoſe glorious treaſure</l>
                  <l>Crowns, Kingdoms, ſweeteſt &amp; eternal pleaſures</l>
                  <l>Which we expect hereafter to poſſeſſe</l>
                  <l>In God himſelf, in heavenly happineſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It is the poore, despiſed, miſerable</l>
                  <l>Mans onely hope to be rich, honorable</l>
                  <l>And happy in the Heavens. The mighty man,</l>
                  <l>The rich, and prosperous with reaſon can</l>
                  <l>Alſo imagine, If he do poſſeſſe</l>
                  <l>In earths prosperity, ſome happineſſe</l>
                  <l>He ſhall be much more happy in thoſe treaſures</l>
                  <l>Thoſe heavenly riches, honour, glory, pleaſures.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let then our ſoules be mounting up aloft</l>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the wings of faith and reaſon, oft.</l>
                  <l>To God, to the Imperiall Heaven, where</l>
                  <l>We ſhall be fill'd with ſweeteſt pleaſures; There</l>
                  <l>Wou'd we have Crowns? Immortall Glory ſhall</l>
                  <l>Environ us, If Thrones? The Imperiall</l>
                  <l>Heaven, ſhall be our footſtool, if treaſures?</l>
                  <l>Eternall riches are with God; If pleaſures?</l>
                  <l>Rivers of pleaſures, various, infinite ſtore</l>
                  <l>There are at his right hand for evermore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:9564:56"/>
                  <l>Let us then with a pitch full of deſire</l>
                  <l>Of love and joy lift up our thoughts, aſpire</l>
                  <l>To thoſe ineſtimable glorious treaſures,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe heavenly Thrones, Crowns, Kingdoms, R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, Pleaſures</l>
                  <l>Let us convert all our vain, vitious</l>
                  <l>Earthly deſires, to the ambitious.</l>
                  <l>Yea covetous, and intemperate deſire</l>
                  <l>(Even to extremes when thus we do aspire)</l>
                  <l>Of heavenly things, herein let us poſſeſſe</l>
                  <l>Our ſouls, even with immoderate happineſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Freely then, let us trace this Paradiſe</l>
                  <l>The Worlds vaſt Palace, let us with our eyes,</l>
                  <l>Our eares, and all our ſences, (ſince we may)</l>
                  <l>The pleaſures therof, cheerfully, enjoy.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Even the meaneſt pleaſures, were (we ſee)</l>
                  <l>Created for this purpoſe, and may be</l>
                  <l>Of excellent uſe, as chirping notes of Birds</l>
                  <l>(Who ſing to pleaſe our eares) the ſame affords</l>
                  <l>Vs prety delectation; when they ſing</l>
                  <l>Who can but pleaſe to hear their warbling.</l>
                  <l>When theſe ſweet birds, doe pleaſe our eares then may</l>
                  <l>We ſweetly contemplate, and think what joy</l>
                  <l>We ſhall poſſeſſe, when full of ſweet deſires</l>
                  <l>We ſhall hear Angels ſing in heavenly Quires.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:9564:57"/>Who with the Muſick of their harmony</l>
                  <l>Shall charm our ſouls, into an extaſie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The fountains alſo, though inſenſible</l>
                  <l>Do ſtrive as farre, as they can poſſible</l>
                  <l>With their ſweet purling murmurs to delight us,</l>
                  <l>So let theſe prety pleaſures, then invite us,</l>
                  <l>To think of heavenly fountains, of that River</l>
                  <l>Which with extrem delights, ſhall fill us ever.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>On earth time, doth produce, joy, for a ſeaſon</l>
                  <l>In Heaven, eternitie, joy, paſt our reaſon,</l>
                  <l>Let tranſitory joy, then puts in minde</l>
                  <l>Of heavenly joys, wherof no end we finde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>On Earth we ſee many and glorious lights,</l>
                  <l>Sun, Moon, Stars, Fire, Cold, other pleaſing ſights</l>
                  <l>And ſhining Beauties, Let us then I pray</l>
                  <l>Think of that glory, which if but one ray</l>
                  <l>We could eſpie, the glittering therof would</l>
                  <l>So dazle our weak eyes, as that we ſhould</l>
                  <l>For ever (like Saint <hi>Peter</hi>) wiſh to bee</l>
                  <l>And dwell where we this glorious ſight may ſee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When we do taſte ſweet liquors, rich and neat,</l>
                  <l>Wine of all ſorts, and curious dainty meat:</l>
                  <l>Let theſe ſweet pleaſures, oftentimes excites us</l>
                  <l>(To which the Angels alſo do invite us)</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="95" facs="tcp:9564:57"/>To think and taſt of that Celeſtiall Feaſt</l>
                  <l>Which ſhall for ever make us, truly bleſt,)</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat feaſt of love and pleaſures, where we may</l>
                  <l>Infinite ſweetneſſe, evermore enjoy.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This heavenly Manna, this celeſtiall food,</l>
                  <l>This divine Nectar, is ſo ſweet, ſo good</l>
                  <l>That if but truly taſte therof, we could</l>
                  <l>(But truly think therof indeed) we ſhould</l>
                  <l>Be ſweetly charm'd into a Rapſody</l>
                  <l>Of heavenly pleaſures, ſuch an extaſie</l>
                  <l>As that we ſhould taſte of, in ſome degree</l>
                  <l>Before hand, Pleaſures of Eternitie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So if we thus can uſe terreſtriall joy;</l>
                  <l>Looking therby to God, to Heaven, we may</l>
                  <l>Enjoy the ſame with happy, heavenly minde,</l>
                  <l>And therby alſo, heavenly joy may finde.</l>
                  <l>So that on earth, already we may even</l>
                  <l>In ſome degree, enjoy delights of Heaven</l>
                  <l>And when this lifes careere, ſhall have an end.</l>
                  <l>From heaven, on earth, to heaven, in heaven aſcend</l>
                  <l>A Paradiſe of pleaſures, ſo we may</l>
                  <l>Both here on earth, and in the heavens enjoy.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
